<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from the north. Otherwise called The conference betvveen Simon Certain, and Pierce Plowman, faithfully collected and gathered by T.F. student</title>
            <author>T. F., student.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118412</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853619</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19011</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 334:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from the north. Otherwise called The conference betvveen Simon Certain, and Pierce Plowman, faithfully collected and gathered by T.F. student</title>
                  <author>T. F., student.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the long shop adioyning vnto S. Mildreds Church in the Pultrie by Iohn Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Francis Thynne.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L⁴.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:1"/>
            <p>Newes from the North.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe called the Conference betvveen Simon Certain, and <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman, faithfully collected and gathered by <hi>T. F. Student.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Aut bibe aut Abi</q>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don at the long shop adioyning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to S. Mildreds Church in the Pultrie by <hi>Iohn Allde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1579.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE PRINTER TO</hi> Simon Certain and Pierce Plowman.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Go foorth Pierce Plowma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, go foorth Sim Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</l>
               <l>right woorthy bothe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation:</l>
               <l>Of your de grees I turn you out for twain,</l>
               <l>ſuch as I neuer found where I haue gon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God let you wax to many thouſands moe,</l>
               <l>that mine eyes may beholde it, and that I:</l>
               <l>May then ſay Lord now let thy Seruant go,</l>
               <l>for then shall I be wel content to dye,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and his ſinguler good Lord Sir Henry Sidney Knight of the moſte Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> Order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord Preſident of <hi>VVales,</hi> &amp; <hi>Marches</hi> of the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there can be no Freendship (right Honorable and myſinguler good Lord) to ſpeak properly vvhere there is no equalitie betvveen the parties, yet may the ſimpleſt and the meaneſt looue and honor the higheſt and greateſt, yea ſomuch the more as their inequalitie is the greater. But that is not properly called freendship but rather a dutyful looue &amp; is harder to be expreſſed and shevved for the inequalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid. For Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndship is betvveen equalls, or at the leaſt vvhere the inequalitie is not ſo very great that the Offices and Duties of Freendship vvhich are the bonds and ſinevvs therof can haue no entercourſe. I ſpeak this for my ſelf that haue long deſired occaſion to shevv my hartie goodvvil and affection vnto your Lordship vvhich hath been ſomevvhat hard for mee to doo for the cauſe abooue remembred. And therfore hauing gathered this little conference: I made bold to dedicate it vnto my good Lord, A thing meeter to be my gift then vvoorthy to be preſented vnto your Honor or to go further vnder the name of ſuch a Patron. Hovv be it, my truſt is that your Lordship of your accuſtomed clemency vvil accept a ſimple thing of him at vvhoſe hands nothing at all vvas looked for, and vvill aloovv my goodvvil tovvards the reparation of ſuch faults and Imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as are heerin.</p>
            <p>So praying God to bleſſe your Lordship and proſper you. From London the tvventie ſix of Nouember. 1579.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships in all humilitie T F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLY AND Gentle READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast heer Godly and gentle <hi>Reader</hi> the Confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwéen <hi>Sim Certain</hi> and <hi>Piere Plovvman</hi> two great Clarks as thou maiſt vnderſtand by their Diſcourſe, which I have gathered &amp; reported as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and as truely as my ſimple memory could retaine the ſame, and that with ſome trauail which I accounted my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Firſt vnto them and others by them héerin mentioned.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly vnto all &amp; euery good man and woman whoſe mindes and harts God may ſturre vp vnto Godlynes and Vertue by their good enſample. Namely all ſuch as are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Maiſters of houſholdes, but chéefly and principally of common Innes and Tauerns whoſe good or euil example ſpreadeth far and wide and I feare in theſe our dayes rather in corruption of life and maners then in edifiyng or increaſe of Vertue and Godlynes according to the ſaying of Ieſus of <hi>Sirack</hi> that it is as hard for a Merchant to be no Lyar and for a Tauerner or Inholder to be no drunkerd which thing although hée hath ſaid to be very hard yet (for the Inholder) that his rule admitteth exception, thou maiſt héer finde with out traueling to <hi>Rippon</hi> in Yorkſhire to learne and ſo for a grote or ſixpence thou maiſt know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which coſt mée abooue fiue marcks to learne beſides my trauail and time ſpent, which yet if it pleaſe thée to accept: I ſhall account right wel beſtowed, which God graunt &amp; that in all thy Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys thy hed ake not before thou alight in ſuch an Hoſtry. Farwel.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Aut bibe aut abi.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:3"/>
            <head>¶ The Printer to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER IF THOV finde any Imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this woork either for the matter in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or els for the diuiſion, the maner and forme therof I truſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wilt allow a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſe aſwel vnto the <hi>Author</hi> as vnto mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thy blame is otherwiſe to be deuided. Thou knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to write &amp; reporte a thing at the mouth of the Speaker aſketh a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umble hand and a great memory, if a man had his Tooles ready for the purpoſe which yet this <hi>Author</hi> had not redy for nothing ſo like as any ſuch matter, and there fore was forced to put his brain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an in truſt with all and to write it in his way homeward.</p>
            <p>In dooing wherof his care was greter to couch the matter truely in ſubſtance then to parte or to deuide or otherwiſe to digeſt the ſame. Which hee referred vnto mee, a which alſo I haue doon as the ſhortnes of the time gaue me leaue. Bothe which excuſes, if it pleaſe thee to admit, thou maiſt in time to come receiue it in more perfection aſwel for his part beeing the matter in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherof I dout not much hath eſcaped him, and alſo for the diuiſion beeing mine.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farwel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:4"/>
            <head>VVM. in commendation of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eauing at large the Brunts of briniſh flood,</l>
               <l>The pitched Feelds and fables finely pend:</l>
               <l>This <hi>Author</hi> héer to doo his Cuntrie good,</l>
               <l>On woork of woorth his time and toile dooth ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The buſie Brain with cankred Enuſe fraught,</l>
               <l>That ſues and ſtriues for ſturring of a ſtraw:</l>
               <l>May read héerin his leſſon largely taught,</l>
               <l>And by the ſame deſcrie him-ſelf a Daw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Countailor, the Spokeſman, and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Who ſimple ſoules to néedleſſe lawing eg:</l>
               <l>May learn héerby ſuch dealings to deteſt,</l>
               <l>As driue poore men their bread with teares to beg.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The prating Sot whoſe peremptory ſpéech,</l>
               <l>Is brayed foorth all Lawyers to defame:</l>
               <l>Not far from hence may finde a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leech.</l>
               <l>To charme his tung and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it in with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in few woord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iny meaning to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Yf you deniaund what mine opinion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Hée hath doon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods bleſſing on his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art</l>
               <l>Who ſend mée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Coelum, non Solum.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>VV. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Antony Munday to all curteous and</hi> freendly <hi>Readers</hi> in commendation of this <hi>VVoork.</hi> ‡</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Tully did of vertuous life define,</l>
               <l>And O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id paint the od conceits of looue:</l>
               <l>And Maro ſquared in a direct line,</l>
               <l>The hard aſſanles that valiant harts did prooue,</l>
               <l>In bloody Battels for their fames behooue,</l>
               <l>As fliering Fortune should them chaunce to pay:</l>
               <l>In vaunting verſe as Maro tels the vvay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But leauing novv at large ſuch fond delights,</l>
               <l>Such Fables fond as pratling Poets vſe:</l>
               <l>This Author heer preſenteth to your ſights,</l>
               <l>Such tales of trueth as may you force to muſe.</l>
               <l>To iudge aright the crime of eche abuſe,</l>
               <l>As heer tvvixt <hi>Sim</hi> and <hi>Pierce</hi> be dooth compound:</l>
               <l>Such vviſe conceits as ſeldome hath been found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen you haue red, Iudge then the Authors paines,</l>
               <l>His tedious toyle in vviſſhing vvel to thee:</l>
               <l>Thy Freendly thanks, he craues no other gaines,</l>
               <l>VVhich vnto him more vvelcome ſure shall bee,</l>
               <l>Then riches ſtore if thou couldſt giue it free.</l>
               <l>VVherfore my Freends doo this at my requeſt:</l>
               <l>To heare and ſee and alvvay ſay the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Honos alit Artes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>A M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:5"/>
            <head>Thomas procter in reporte of the Authors good vvil</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the moorthy Woorks,</l>
               <l>which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arued <hi>Tully</hi> pend:</l>
               <l>The care of Cuntrie and of freends.</l>
               <l>hee greatly dooth commend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Which leſſon in my minde,</l>
               <l>the Man which took in hand.</l>
               <l>To pen this pleſant Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>did perfect vnderſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For in the ſame hee ſhowes,</l>
               <l>a looue vnto his Frends:</l>
               <l>Beſide a zealous minde of good,</l>
               <l>that to his Cuntrie tends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Of <hi>Louers</hi> liues, of <hi>vvarres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ne yet of <hi>vvunders</hi> great:</l>
               <l>Hee ſeemes to publiſh vnto vs.</l>
               <l>but ſimply dooth intreat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Of ſilly Men, whoſe proof,</l>
               <l>dooth ſuch experience giue:</l>
               <l>As for Examples of our lines,</l>
               <l>learnes eche eſtate to liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Wherin the <hi>Author</hi> ſought,</l>
               <l>ſuch meanes to publiſh it:</l>
               <l>As in my ſimple Iudgement ſure,</l>
               <l>might ſeem to prooue his Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But for the careful paines,</l>
               <l>which he hath ſpent heerin:</l>
               <l>Hee only craues for recompence,</l>
               <l>your fauours good to win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Wherby you may him mooue, <note place="margin">‡‡</note>
               </l>
               <l>to vtter his good wil:</l>
               <l>When as occaſion ſhall him ſerue,</l>
               <l>in woorks of greater ſkil.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Nil melius Arte;</q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>T P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:5"/>
            <head>Iohn Peeterhouſe to the Reporter of this Hiſtory.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that haſt reported this pleaſant Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>Wherof thine eyes and eares are a witneſſe:</l>
               <l>And haſt intreaſured the memory,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pierce</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> for their woorthines,</l>
               <l>Withouten hope of hire or recompence:</l>
               <l>For thy long iourney, or for thy diſpence,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Thou haſt acquit thy dutie vnto them,</l>
               <l>In this behalf, and if I geſſe aright:</l>
               <l>Thou haſt deſerued well of other men,</l>
               <l>Before whom thou haſt ſet a Candle light.</l>
               <l>Of Nurture and of Education:</l>
               <l>By men of baſe and meane condition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Which ſome for that cauſe wil eſtéeme the leſſe,</l>
               <l>Hauing reſpect vnto the circumſtaunce:</l>
               <l>The great apparaunce of vnlikelyneſſe,</l>
               <l>Waying all others in their owne ballaunce.</l>
               <l>As if that God could not reſerue a few:</l>
               <l>Such as him liſt his glory for to ſhew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For what though this age vniuerſally,</l>
               <l>Séemeth giuen ouer to corruption:</l>
               <l>Séemed it not ſo in the dayes of <hi>Elie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When yet God had reſerued many a one?</l>
               <l>So hath he now, that are not gon aſide:</l>
               <l>Nor ſolde them ſelues to Couetiſe and Pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ As thou haſt well ſhewed in this Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>What by thine owne proofe and experience:</l>
               <l>What by thine Hoſte <hi>Simons</hi> authoritie,</l>
               <l>Which (for mine owne part) I doo reuerence.</l>
               <l>And therfore (I ſay) thank come to thy hand:</l>
               <l>That haſt it giuen vs to vnderſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And putteſt vs in hope that Charitie,</l>
               <l>Is not ſtark dead, though ſhe be wounded ſore:</l>
               <l>By Pride and Couetiſe her enemye,</l>
               <l>And that our God yet kéepeth ſome in ſtore.</l>
               <l>That bothe in déed and woord doo ſéeke his praiſe:</l>
               <l>God let them wax and giue them happy dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_his_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:6"/>
            <head>¶ The Reporter to his Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>My little Book where ſo thou chaunce to dwel,</l>
               <l>God giue thee fauour in thy Readers ſight:</l>
               <l>Whom if thou pleaſe all, thou muſt quit thee well,</l>
               <l>And better then I feare is in thy might.</l>
               <l>For that dooth ſeldome chaunce to any one:</l>
               <l>Better or wurſe without exception.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ If any man or Woman chalenge thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>For any woord or any argument:</l>
               <l>Come not to ſeek thy defence at me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>For I am not thine Author verament.</l>
               <l>Get thee into the North to <hi>Rippon</hi> Town:</l>
               <l>And there enquire for <hi>Pierce</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> woorthy Clown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ And eke for <hi>Simon Certaine</hi> at the Signe,</l>
               <l>Of the Greek <hi>Omega,</hi> there dooth he dwell:</l>
               <l>Where welcome thou ſhalt be as I diuine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Aſke them whether thou haue reported well.</l>
               <l>Their Conference according to the trueth:</l>
               <l>If they ſay yea, of others haue no rueth.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:6"/>
            <head>Hovv the Author comming homevvard out of Scotland through Yorkshire, chaunced to lodge in Rippon. At vvhat ſigne, the name of the Hoſte, the order and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Houſe and Family. And his entertaynment there. Chap 1.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my laſt return from Edenbrough in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, comming homeward through York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire: I traueled ſomewhat out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon high London way of purpoſe to ſée the Countrie. And one day among others, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euen: I chaunced to come to a little through fare Town called <hi>Rippon,</hi> where at the very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the town I met a poore olde Woman, of whom I aſked if there were any good lodging in the town. She anſwe red me, that there was good lodging at the Signe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Gréek <hi>Omega.</hi> The Gréek <hi>Omega</hi> (quoth I) What doo you mean by that? Nothing ſaid ſhe, but that there is good lodging and honeſt entertainment which (I ſuppoſe) is all that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Then I aſked her what was the Good mans name of the houſe. His name (quoth ſhe) is <hi>Simon Certain,</hi> we call him commonly <hi>Sim Certain, Sim Certain</hi> (quoth I) ſurely theſe are very ſtraunge names, and ſo bidding her farewell: I departed into the town ward, much more deſirous to be come to my lodging, for the ſtraungenes of the names, aſwel of the Signe: as alſo of the Good man of the Houſe. By that time I had entred a little way into the town: I was ware of a very faire Greek <hi>Omega,</hi> hanging foorth as a common Signe, euen as the olde Woman had tolde me befors. And thither I went, and entring into the houſe: I found in the Hall the Good man, his two Sonnes, his Chamberlain, and his Hoſtler ſinging the C iiij. Pſalme of Dauid very diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and orderly. The Goodwife with her two Daughters ſat ſpinning at their Whéeles a little diſtaunce from them. All which things when I behéeld: I thought with my ſelf that theſe things were yet more ſtraunge to beholde, then were
<pb facs="tcp:19011:7"/> either the Signe or els the Good mans name to heare. So I had them God ſpéed. The Hoſte very courteouſly aroſe, and had me welcome, ſo did the wife alſo, and aſked me whether I meant to tary all night. I anſwered yea. Then he aſked me if I would ſée my Chamber. No gentle Hoſte (quoth I) I will not hinder ſo much you good exerſiſe, for I am ſure I cannot be lodged amiſſe in this houſe. Not ſo Sir (quoth he) but ye ſhall haue the beſt that we haue and welcome. I gaue him hartye thanks. Then he enquired of me, of whence I was, where I had béene, and whither I was bound. I tolde him I was a Southern man borne and dwelling, and that I had béene at <hi>Edenborough</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was thus farre in my way homeward. In good time Sir (quoth he) and yée are hartily welcome into this part of Yorkſhire. I thank you gentle Hoſte (quoth I.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>The comming thither of Pierce Plovvman, beeing nevvly come from London. His requeſt to the Hoſte to lend him fiue pound vppon a pavvn. The refuſall of the Hoſte, the queſtion thereupon mooued, beeing the matter of the Conference. Chap. 2.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y that time we had talked ſcant half an hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: there came in a Countrie man a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, a tolly olde fatherly man, bringing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his arme a fardel of Bookes, as many as be might well holde vndernethe one of his armes, he gaue vs the time of the day. What Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) welcome from Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sir (quoth he to me) this Neighbour of mine is lately come from where you are going God willing. Truely (quoth I) and this is happily met by grace of God, and as I verily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe néere in the mid way betwéene <hi>Edenbrough</hi> and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. With that Neighbour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imon quoth this <hi>Pierce plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (for that was his name) I am come to deſire your help. What is the matter Neighbour Pierce (quoth our Hoſte?)
<pb facs="tcp:19011:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Neighbour (quoth he) to lend me fiue pound for half a yéer, for truely (quoth he) I haue ſpent all my mony at London, and haue not left my ſelf ſo much as to buy my ſéed Wheat, wherwith to ſowe my land this ſeaſon. No haue neighbour <hi>Pierce?</hi> (quoth he) that was very il handled, ye ſhould alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes ſo vſe your matters that the main ſtock be ſaued whole. Fye neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth ve, ſpeak no more of that for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reuerence of God, for truely I am aſhamed of my ſelf, but what remedie now ſaue patience, and to learne to be wiſer héerafter, What meanes all theſe paper Books (quoth our Hoſte. Mary neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> they ſhalbe ſuretie vn to you for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>paiment of your fiue pound. With that they were vnbound, and béeing opened &amp; looked vpon: they were Billes, Anſwers, Replications, Reioinders Copies of Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and ſuch like. Some out of one Court, ſome out of an other. When our Hoſte had ſéene them all: why Neighbour (quoth he) doo you think to méet with any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is ſo mad to lend v. pence vpon ſuch traſh? Traſh neighbour quoth <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erce:</hi> they ſtand me in abooue fiftie pound. Peraduentnre ſo quoth our Hoſte, but that prooueth not that they are woorth fiftie points, ſauing vnto him that were as mad to buy them of you: as you bought them at their hands that ſolde them vnto you. But or you méet with any ſuch chapma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I beléeue you will be weary of kéeping them. With that <hi>Pierce</hi> began to be half offended. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, fiue pound is a ſmall matter betwéene vs twaine, you ſhall haue it vpon your woord. But as for your Books: héere dwelleth a Lady not far hence, cary them to her, for they are far f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and déere bought, and ſuch things (men ſay) are good for Ladyes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce findeth it ſtraunge that men should pay ſo deere for thinges, vvhich in their handes are ſo vile and little vvoorth, as concerning their return. Chap. 3.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:8"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> I can put vp that mock at your hands, for I knowe ya meane me no euill but good therby, but veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly me thinketh it ſtandeth hardly with their exiſtimation that will be holden and termed woorſhipfull yea honorable, to take ſo extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely for things, wherof no better return is to be made, yet muſt we pay them with great attendaunce, with cap in hand and all reuerence. Great reaſon quoth our Hoſte, for they are woorſhipfull, and right woorthye of all thoſe duties. Then haue I béene in an errour a long time (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> for I haue alwayes hitherto thought that woorſhip and honor had ſtood in giuing: I not in taking, in helping, reléeuing and doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good: and not in their contraryes, and this ſéemeth vnto me bothe reaſonable and alſo common experience, for we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God at whoſe hands we receiue all goodnes, and therfore properly vnto him is all honor and woorſhip due, and vnto men but ſo far foorth as they approchen vnto God in qualitie of vertue, iuſtice, mercy and other goodnes, wherfore in all reaſon he ought to be moſte honorable and woorſhipfull that dooth the moſte good, and vnto the greateſt number, for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in my diſcretion, the woorſhip and the gaine ought to be deuided, and he that gayneth, or is reléeued, and is holpen: ought to honor and woorſhip him by whom he gayneth, is hot pen and reléeued, for otherwiſe why dooth Seruant woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip his Maiſter &amp; not <hi>e conuerſo.</hi> Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Noſte, our honorable &amp; reuerend forefathers with great wiſdeme and diſcretion affeſſed theſe fées and charges, and that for the great zeale and looue which they bare vnto God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and vertue, and to the perſons quallified therwith.</p>
            <p>With that <hi>Pierce</hi> clapped his hand vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boord. I make God a vow (quoth he) what ſo euer he was that firſt praiſed a ſhéet of paper with twelue lines written therin at eight pence, nay at xij. pence, for I am ſure I haue CC. that coſt me after that rate, he was neither fréend to godlines ne vertue, to God neither to Good man or woman. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, this is but the errour of your iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:19011:8"/> and that ſhall appéere vnto you ſo euidently, that your ſelf ſhall confeſſe that theſe fées and charges which you think ſo great and ſo exceſſiue had ſo great reaſon in their beginning: as that greater had neuer any ciuil ordinance or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution. Whether yée wil regarde the honor and glory of God or the preſeruation of the common Welth which chéefly dependeth therupon. That ſéemeth wunderful ſtrange vnto mée (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> that in ſuch extreame taking and ſo ſmall ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dring there ſhould lye hidden ſo great miſtery of good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and therfore gladly would I heare your reaſons ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. Very wel Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) then I will take in hand to prooue it vnto you, which I truſt I ſhall doo ſufficiently: if I can prooue theſe are no proper nor priuate gain or proffit, but a publique and a common treaſure to the eaſe and reléef of the whole common Welth and of the beſt &amp; godlyeſt Members of the ſame, yea verily (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel (quoth our Hoaſt.)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Simon approoueth their great Fees and Charges as things ment, to be a revvard and nurishment of Knovve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Learning and Vertue, and punishment of vngodli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and vice, and therfore true and iuſt. Cap. 4.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt I think yée wil graunt (quoth hée) that Magiſtrates and Officers are the Deputies and Leiutenaunts of GOD héer in Earth, high and honorable, for that they are in very déed the hand and mouth of the Law, and in fewe &amp; plaine woords the ſpeaking &amp; woork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Law, for by them the law commaundeth and forbiddeth. So that their end and purpoſe is that God may be honored and glorified, good and godly People cheriſhed, ſhortly that peace and concord may be maintained, I graunt you all this (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> you will graunt (quoth hée) that the way and mean to woork all theſe things is to puniſh and chaſtice the wicked and the vngodly, and to giue as little fauour vnto ſinne as is poſſible, that is very true alſo (quoth <hi>Pierce.)</hi> Yée will graunt quoth our Hoaſt that the wayes and meanes to
<pb facs="tcp:19011:9"/> puniſh ſinnes &amp; wickednes are diuers, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the offence, as ſome by death, ſome by other punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body greater or ſmaller. And that there is alſo a pecuniall puniſhment by the purſſe, as by fine and ranſome, and ſuch like. I graunt you all this quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> You will graunt me alſo (quoth he) that all puniſhments are gréeuous vnto the ſufferers therof, neither are or ought to be pleaſant vnto the dooers and executors. That is very true alſo quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> except they be wicked perſons bothe the ſufferer and the executor. Then quoth our Hoſte, ſéeing all puniſhments are fear full and gréeuous vnto the ſufferer therof, &amp; no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but rather ſorowe and gréefe of hart vnto the erecutors therof: ſuch and ſo muſt néeds be the firſt cauſes and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therof. That is very true quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> You knowe quoth our Hoſte, that the cauſes and occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of puniſhment is ſin, wickednes and miſgouernment of life, for the woord of God telleth vs, that the reward of ſinne is death. All that is very true quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> Very well then quoth our Hoſte, theſe Propoſitions which you haue graunted: doo ſuffiſe for the matter which I haue taken in hand to prooue, which is, that theſe great Fées and charges were neuer ment, nor yet are receiued or conuerted into priuate or proper vſe. I pray you Neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> let me heare how it is prooued, for I promiſe you faithfully for any thing I haue yet herd: your prooues are farther to fet.</p>
            <p>You knowe quoth our Hoſte, that the nature of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooly is to be quarelous and contencious, and dayly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one an other, and alſo to take no wrong &amp; doo no right. That is very true quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> You knowe quoth our Hoſt that the common weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher with they wil be aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vpon eche other is the Law, which indéed is the Magiſtrate, as ye haue already graunted, ſo that vpon the matter: he is made the executor of their wilfulnes and vengeaunce, which they will néeds doo vpon eche other, which thing you haue alredy confeſſed to be gréeuous and vnpleaſant to euery good man. Therfore hath it euer béen, and yet is thought, and that very wiſely and truely, that the likelieſt way &amp; meane to diſſwade
<pb facs="tcp:19011:9"/> their wilfulnes which no reaſon, looue nor feare of GOD could diſſwade was to make their wilfulnes as déere and as heauy vnto them as reaſonably might be doon, to the end that they ſhould not ſo lightly and for euery trifle ver and trouble bothe the Magiſtrate &amp; one an other, which effect although it failed to woork, &amp; that their madnes would not be reſtrayned therby: that yet their vngodlines might return to the profit and reléefe of others their Neighbours &amp; Brethern that were better affected, &amp; ſo by one ſelf and ſame meane: the vngodly puniſhed &amp; fléeced, and the godly amended &amp; inriched therby, &amp; that this was their meaning y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was the firſt aſſeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: common experience teacheth vs, for in néedfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary actions, as debt, detinew, and account and ſuch like: the charges are ſo reaſonable, as that no man would in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience giue leſſe.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, for that they are actions of common right, and ſuch as muſt néeds day by day ariſe betwéene a man and his Brother, neither doo they diſhoneſt either of the parties, which I dare not affirm vpon actions vpon caſes, neither did they ſo iudge of them, as I verily beléeue, and therfore did they ſet double and treble charges thereupon, for greater is the charges in a brabble for a woord ſpoken: then for thrée hundred pound of honeſt det.</p>
            <p>So that the Magiſtrate, who for ſuch Ale houſe actions and brabbles: ſhould otherwiſe neuer be at reſt, except he ſhould deny them his help, which might be ſlaunderous and perillous to the whole eſtate.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate I ſay of pure pittie and compaſſion was forced to ſet great charges vpon them, for the ſmall fauour that he bare vnto them, &amp; vnto their firſt cauſes &amp; occaſions.</p>
            <p>The greatnes of all which charges not withſtanding, yet doo we dayly ſée how the vngodly run togither by heaps like brute beaſts, and yet I dare ſafely ſay, that by the greatnes of theſe charges, and the terrour therof: many a brabling matter hath béene and is dayly put vp without any reuenge ſought therof, and many a one hauing purſued and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his action, yet haue his charges ſo gallded him: that
<pb facs="tcp:19011:10"/> he hath béene eaſier to deale with all his life after. And ſo by this meane many a wilfull body brought to knowe him ſelf, and to honor God therby.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> but I my ſelf haue had two or thrée brabbles that haue kept me dooing theſe ſeuen yéeres, in which time I am ſure I haue ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booue fiftie pound, beſide my charges to and fro, loſſe of time, and my hinderaunce at home. And what haue ye gotten for all this? quoth our Hoſte. Theſe papers quoth he. Wel woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th fiftie points quoth our Hoſte. I think verily quoth our Hoſte if any honeſt Neighbour had néeded to haue borowed ten Pound therof: you would not haue it ſo ready to haue pleaſured him withall. If I ſhould ſay truely (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> I think the very ſame. What are you aſſeſſed vnto the poore in your pariſh quoth our Hoſte? A peny a wéek quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> And think you that enough quoth our Hoſte? Yea verily quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi> Loe Sir quoth our Hoſte, whether commeth this vnto my ſaying and maintenaunce of theſe great Fées and charges or not? Who can deny the excellency of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution? wherby the Couetous vngodly men are ſhot one againſt an other, and doo puniſh eche other, and wherby alſo ſo plentiful prouiſion is made for the godly poore at their charges, and yet no thank to them therfore, and that thoſe things from the which they would depart vnto any Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or godly vſe or purpoſe, with as good will as from their eyes to be plucked out of their heads, or their tripes out of their bellyes, by this meane vndeſired of their owne accord, they bring it in by handfuls, &amp; ſo as it hath béene ſayd, plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful prouiſion made for their godly Neighbours at their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and yet no thank vnto them therfore.</p>
            <p>Call you this a prouiding for the poore? Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> I would I had giuen you the beſt horſe in my Plou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh to make this ſaying true, and I ſwere to you (quoth he) prooue it true: and you ſhall haue him yet or this day Seuen night, for that would caſe my hart if I might perceiue that any godly perſon hath fared the better or were amended by any parte of all my great expences. For then yet ſhould I
<pb facs="tcp:19011:10"/> think that I haue doone ſome good with all the loſſe of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Why Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth <hi>Simon)</hi> doo you doubt that all theſe ſommes or the greateſt part therof: commeth not to the vſe of the common welth, and to the reléefe and ſuſtenaunce of the godly poore, and other eaſements of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things in maintenaunce of the common Welth? Nay Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth he) I dout it not, for I am fully perſwaded the contrary. Truely Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth he) this is an vncharitable and a very erronious oppinion, and that I will prooue vnto you by reaſons manifeſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, &amp; ſuch as your ſelf haue alredy graunted &amp; confeſſed. I pray you neighbour <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> let me heare how:</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Simon approoueth theſe fees and charges as publique and not priuate, by argument taken from effects vnto their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Chap. 5.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer he be that Coueteth priuately to gaine and profit by any thing (quoth our Hoſte) coueteth the thing wherby he gayu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and profiteth, this is ſo true (quoth he) that I will not deſire you to graunt it vnto me, for it is a neceſſary argument from the effect vnto the cauſe, and therfore if ye will affirm that the Magiſtrate and officer coueteth theſe great fées and charges and priuately to thriue and wax rich therby: you muſt nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarily conclude, that he fauoureth all the firſt &amp; mean cauſes therof, which were a horrible &amp; a fearfull concluſion; &amp; yet as I haue ſaid followeth neceſſarily vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> premiſſes granted, &amp; therfore is couetiſe ſo much more odious &amp; deteſtable in a Magiſtrate then in a common perſon, for couetiſe as he excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all other vices ſimply conſidered: euen ſo reſpectiuely he excéedeth him ſelf, I ſay reſpectiuely to wit, qualified by the perſon in whom he dwelleth, for in a priuat perſon: he is but a priuat ſin, &amp; exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vnto his M. only, but in a Magiſtrate he is a publique &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erall corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> people, for ther is no couetoꝰ perſon béeing but a priuat man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any other to be ſuch as they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues are, the reaſon is, for that the Couetiſe of others: is nothing whereby they
<pb facs="tcp:19011:11"/> ſhould gayne or be aduaunced, but rather loſe therby.</p>
            <p>Therfore could they be content that there were few or no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch as they are, wherby it appéereth that couetiſe in a priuate Perſon neither woorketh nor wiſheth any general corruption and yet fulfilleth the talent and habit of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and ſo much the more. The very ſame is to be ſaid of all other vices in all other perſons without exception of degrée, as Whoordome, Pride, Gluttony, Drunkennes and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exceſſe in voluptuous pleſure, in all which things what ſoeuer hath or euer had the greateſt felicitie and enioyd moſt therof yet would they not that others did the like, or at the leaſt no moe then they them ſelues muſt neceſſarily vſe for for tha'ccompliſhment of their pleaſures which requireth ſome company. The reaſon is already ſhewed to wit for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other Folkes pleaſures are not their pleaſures, neither doo increaſe the ſame, but rather their paines and miſery.</p>
            <p>For the hunger, ſcarcitie and want of others giueth a good taſte and ſauour vnto the voluptuouſnes and pleaſures of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vngodly, and therfore could they be very wel content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their owne wickednes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, for pleaſure haue they none nor gain in the lewdnes or the miſgouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of other. And if they had: yet want they power to corrupt others ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by otherwiſe then by example which can not doo much in any one priuate man or woman, for that they haue but the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their owne liues. But of Couetiſe in the Magiſtrat it is otherwiſe, for hée hath the leading and the fourming of other mens liues and therfore differeth from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and priuat perſon bothe concerning his wil and alſo concerning his habititie and power to execute the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt concerning deſire and will hée cannot wiſh that the common people ſhould be godly and vertuous, for neither ſtandeth his great gain, nor his Ambition therin, for why they are two things incompatible and contrary.</p>
            <p>Then concerning his power to execute his wil and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire: it is ſo great and ſo mightie that the olde Proouers hath not douted to call the common People the Image of their Magiſtrates and officers for as certainly as this antecedent.</p>
            <p>The man cateth and drinketh inferreth this conſequent
<pb facs="tcp:19011:11"/> the man is a liue: euen ſo certainly this propoſition the Magiſtrates &amp; officers are couetous inferreth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion.</p>
            <p>The People are vngratious and vngodly. The reaſon is peremptory for the Magiſtrate and Officer hath the Bridls rain in his hand either to giue libertie vnto vngodlynes and diſſolution of life: orels to refrain the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now all men may dayly ſée by proof that there is no wilde Beaſt ſo very brute and barbarous as man will wax and bée through libertie and that for the excellencie of his nature booue all other Creatures and his great vnderſtanding in good and euil.</p>
            <p>¶ And therfore to admit in a Magiſtrate a couetiſe and a deſire of priuate and proper gain, Namely by fées and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aryſing and growing as is alredy confeſſed: theſe were to conclude an odious and deteſtable Conſequence againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrate and Officer of whome wée are forbidden by God to ſpeak or think ſaue all honor and reuerence.</p>
            <p>¶ Wherfore I ſay it ſtandeth not with the reuerend and honourable opinion that wée are bound to haue of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to ſay or to think that theſe great gains and fées doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him in priuate and proper vſe, but rather to Judge &amp; think that the Magiſtrate &amp; Officer receiueth them as thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> excommunicat and as a common Treaſure dedicated vnto godly vſes and purpoſes in eaſe and reléef of the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth.</p>
            <p>¶ Would God this were true quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> for I dare lay my life (quoth hée) that if all the ſums of money that are leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhamefully ſpent in one Terme about vain ſutes and brabbles were reſerued and accounted in the end of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Term: they would amount to more then all the Collection for the Poore through out all the pariſhes in England for half a yéer, neuertheleſſe many a one thinketh him ſelf ſore charged, namely my ſelf God forgiue mée.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (quoth our Hoaſt) I am of no other Opinion, neither doo I Judge that all theſe great Fées and Reuenues are any other thing but a Collection for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and intents aforeſaid, neither that the Receiuers of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19011:12"/> ſame doo differ from thoſe other Collectors in Pariſh Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſauing in the greatnes of their receit and alſo ſauing that they are not forced to craue it at the parties hands and ſome time to conuent him before a Iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of peace for a grote or ſix pence as the others oft times are, And alſo ſauing that for their reuerend and honorable eſtemation they are not accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Sauing vnto the Lord God the Author generall and vnto their owne Conſciences.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce denyeth the reaſons alleaged as probable but not neceſſary, his reaſons therfore. Cap. 6.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged many fair and coulorable propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and concluſions and haue gon about mée w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this reaſon and with that.</p>
            <p>I am no Schoole man, Neighbour quoth hée, but yet ſome reaſon I haue and ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I haue ſéen, and ſome héed I haue taken thereof, wherfore if you wil giue mée leaue to anſwere you: you ſhal hear mée as probably diſprooue theſe your allegations as you prooued them, for I ſhall prooue all your propoſitions are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and not neceſſary, neither doo inferre a neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion as you haue pretended, For the better dooing wherof: firſt for orders ſake, I wil reherce your propoſitions, reaſons and arguments, wherof the firſt is: that the Magiſtrate and Officer is to be had in all honor and reuerence becauſe hée is the Law which is moſte honorable and reuerend, this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as an vndouted trueth, namely for that the end aſwel of the one as of the other, is that God may be honored and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, godly People cheriſhed. and maintain peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſtrengthned and furthered, wherupon ſtandeth the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie &amp; the good eſtate of all Cuntries and common welths, their wayes and meanes you haue alleaged are theſe.</p>
            <p>To puniſh and chaſtice the wicked and the vngodly, and to reſtrain their libertie as much as is poſſible. Yée haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alleaged that puniſhments are diuers, ſome corporall,
<pb facs="tcp:19011:12"/> ſome pecuniall, and that that all puniſhments are gréeuous bothe vnto the ſufferers, and alſo vnto the dooers therof, but that I will not graunt ye without diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Very true it is that all puniſhments without exception, are greeuous vnto the ſufferers therof, but vnto the executor therof: they are not all ſo, namely ſuch as are pecuniall and the gaine therof returning vnto the executor. For although that to beat, burn, hang or whip any creature of God, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Chriſtian man or woman: is an odious thing, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no good or Godly hart can haue pleaſure: yet for aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſake it is often otherwiſe, for otherwiſe there would not ſo many Oxen, Shéep and Calues be murthered, and ſo few Hogs, Dogs or Cats, their offences béeing only their good fleſh.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, although that in all Godly reaſon your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments haue great neceſſitie: yet in humaine reaſon and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience it hath butb are probabilitie and is no more. But as if for example you wil ſay Women ought to be aſhamed to be ſéene bibbing Wine in common Tauerns, or to be ſéen at common laſciuious and bawdie Stage Playes: therfore they are aſhamed therof.</p>
            <p>This is an argument gathered from <hi>poſſe</hi> to <hi>eſſe,</hi> to wit, from ſhould or ought to be, to is ſimply, and hath not any neceſſitie nor firmitie, and that ſhall you ſée if you will goe with me to London this next terme.</p>
            <p>How be it, you ſéeme to inforce your antecedent, by the honorable exiſtimation wherin I am bound to haue the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Officer, and therby you think that of dutie I ought to graunt it you for the ſhamefull conſequence which neceſſarily enſueth vpon the denyall therof.</p>
            <p>Truely that not withſtanding, me thinketh all this but a very bare and naked proofe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:13"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Simon maintaineth his aſſertion by authoritie of holy Scripture and diuerſitie taken betvveen the revvarde of Vertue, Learning and Knovvledge and the hire of ſeruile trauail and labour. Cap. 7.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>All you this a bare and naked proof Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſt if you, denye this proof (quoth hée) you reuerſe &amp; ouerthrow all humain ſocietie which is maintained and vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by giuing vnto God y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which is due vnto God, and vnto man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is due vnto Man. But vnto God what can wée giue ſaue honor, prayſe &amp; glory, firſt and immediatly vnto him ſelf, and ſecondly vnto his Deputies and Lieutenaunts, to wit, Magiſtrates &amp; Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whoſe calling and appointing therunto as it is of God: ſo muſt and ought wée to think that it is for their godlynes and vertues, for God him ſelf hath ſaid them that honor mée I will honor, and they that diſhonour mée I will diſhonour, wherfore our wiſe and reuerend Elders and Forefathers in their aſſeſſing theſe great Fées and charges: did mean to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor them whome God honoured. And therfore vnto their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings appoited they great and honorable reuenues, knowing that their gain is the puniſhment of vice and the rewarde of Vertue, and that the part &amp; portion of all the godly is therin, knowing alſo that there is not ſo great Incouragement vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Vertue and Godlynes: as the liberall rewarde therof, and that all vngodlynes and vnthankfulnes is meaſured by the greatnes of the goodnes and benefit receiued either at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> handꝭ of God or man. Laſtly knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they might not proſecute but perſecute the cauſes &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theſe gains as hath alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy béen prooued, and therfore I ſay abooue all common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcretion they aſſeſſed theſe Fées and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euenues that the gains might be great and yet the cauſes therof few, quite contrary to all other eſtates and faculties, for what other reaſon is there that one man ſhall labour fore a whole day &amp; at night ſhall receiue twelue pence or eight pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his hire: An other for half or a quarter of an houres eaſie trauail ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:19011:13"/> receiue xx. ſhillings or ſometime more, what is the cauſe of this diuerſitie? euen this, the one is a hire and a price of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile labour and trauell, and is receiued in proper and priuat vſe, the other is an honor doone vnto vertue, Godlineſſe and knowledge: which doo receiue nor holde, or account any ſo baſe things proper or priuat, or can be ſo baſely minded, as to ioy therin, further then they may glorify God therby.</p>
            <p>What other reaſon is there, that one man in the return of a Reame of paper, ſhall gaine xij. pence or xvi. pence cléer, and yet where he layd out ij. pence: the other layd out x. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And after the ſame rate in Wax, that one man ſhall ſell more for vi. pence: then an other ſhall ſell for viij. pound, which neuertheleſſe bought as déere as he, within xy. pence at xx. ſhillings waring, and bothe layd out more mony, &amp; lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger looked for the return therof. I ſay theris no reaſon other then is already made.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce denyeth the calling to office, to be ſuch as Simon hath alledged. Chap. 8.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> wheras you maintaine your aſſerſion by the woorthines of the Magiſtrate and Officer, and doo inſiſt therupon, alledging that they are called by God, and that for their godlines and vertue. The firſt part I greatly dout, for that many of them buy their offices, and pay very déerely therfore, yea ſome ſell their very inheritaunces for that purpoſe, I mean to buy offices, now did I neuer read that euer God receiued Money for an office, how be it I refer my ſelf héerein to my Maiſters that are learned.</p>
            <p>The next part that they are called for their Vertue and Godlines, ſurely then I verily ſuppoſe ſome of them are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the things that neuer were in them before, and then were the caller deceiued, which God cannot be, except you will ſay that God of his méere goodnes and mercy called them
<pb facs="tcp:19011:14"/> for the vertues and godlines which he meaneth to call them vnto, and in this order beginneth to woork, I meane in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing vpon them ſo liberally, &amp; by that meanes to charge them with his expectation, in reſpect of their great Talent committed vnto them, which thing you ſéeme to alledge, as no ſmall cauſe and conſideration of the high aſſeſſing of the fees and charges aforeſayd, and that ſo great mercies &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beſtowed vpon them by God, and ſo liberall reward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto them by men: ſhould ſuffiſe to make them god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and verteous from thence foorth: what ſo euer they were or had béene before. All which arguments, although they be godly and probable: yet as I ſayd before they ſtand doutful, for the olde Prouerb, Honors chaunge maners. I beléeue the godly and the learned doo dout whether it be taken in the better part, or in the wurſe, for I am very ſure, that many are wurſe diſpoſed, and much more vngodly in high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable calling: then while they were in meane eſtate and degrée. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) there is no ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſo generall, that it admitteth not exception, albeit I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out not nor euer did, that honors chaunge maners, is and euer was meant in the better part. For the wiſe man ſaith. He that is vngodly in welth: how much more vngodly would he be in pouertie? The examples are many that doo prooue that honors chaunge men to the better, namely of <hi>Saule,</hi> of whom it is ſaid that béeing called from a ſimple boy after his Inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration: he felt him ſelf ſudenly chaunged, and as the book ſaith: he felt a new hart in him.</p>
            <p>The like examples we haue of many Kings &amp; Prophets in the holy Scripture. But to come néerer, bothe for the time and alſo the place, in our Engliſh Hiſtory we read of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble King H. the fifth, who in his Fathers life was of euill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and kept company with riotors and vnthrifts, ſo that there was ſmall hope of him, but after the death of H. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth. when this yung man was placed in his kingdom: he ſent for all his olde companions, who were not a little glad therof, but when they weare come into his preſence: he ſharply rebuked them, and giuing them ſmall rewards, yet
<pb facs="tcp:19011:14"/> better then he thought them woorthy, he forbad them during their liues to come within xij. miles of the Court, and that vpon great penaltie. All theſe examples doo manifeſtly proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, that liberall reward of vertue, and high and Honorable calling doo increaſe vertue in them in whom it is alredy, and cauſeth them in whom it is not ſaue only in apparaunce, yet for pure ſhame to imbrace it, ſéeing that otherwiſe hot coales are heaped vppon their heads, through their ſhameleſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes vnto them that haue ſo thorowly prouoked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the greatnes of their benefits.</p>
            <p>And therfore againſt all theſe reaſons and proofs, to ſay that the Magiſtrate and Officer ſhould priuatly Couet and conuert ſo great ſummes of treaſure: it were to ſhamefull and ſlaunderous, conſidered that they are the effects of ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cauſes as hath already béene ſhewed. And conſidered alſo the horrible and wicked concluſion that would enſue therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as alſo hath already béene prooued.</p>
            <p>Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> neuer tell me what might or dooth inſue therupon: but conſider the trueth and the matter as it is in déed. And if theſe great fées and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doo not come vnto their receiuers and takers in proper and priuate: what mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they to make ſo great labour, ſute, fréendſhip and coſt to get thoſe offices and callings. And how commeth it to paſſe that by the meanes of ſuch offices: ſuch as before were of ſmall habilitie, come to purchaſe a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons liuing, yea twaine or thrée. Shortly, that their care is greater to heare and learne where any Land or Lordſhip is to be ſolde: then for the Money wherewith to purchaſe the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>Simon confirmeth his aſſertion touching the deſire to beare office to be good, by the Etimologie and expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vvoord <hi>Officium.</hi> Chap. 9.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:15"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoaſt) all theſe matters are eaſily deuided, vnto the which thus I anſwere. To the firſt which is their great deſire to be in ſuch Offices of receit, I ſay you miſiudge of their deſire becauſe you doo not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the meaning of this woord Office and doo think him to be an Engliſh man wheras in very déed his Father is an <hi>Italian,</hi> whoſe proper ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and meaning you doo not vnderſtand, for in our Engliſh tung Office is no more to ſay nor nothing els but Seruice, ſo that whoſoeuer deſireth an Office hée deſireth to doo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice orles a place wherin to doo ſeruice, now all men knowe that a priuate man is not able to compare with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Officer in abilitie and power. Therfore to deſire an Office is to deſire to be better abled, to expreſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the hartie goodwil and affection which hée hath to bée ſeruiceable vnto God and his common welth, for that in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat eſtate his power anſwereth not vnto his goodwil therin, and therfore the better man the more deſirous to be in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffice and in the more Offices, for the greater is his power to ſhew his good affection towards God who is the Giuer of all theſe things.</p>
            <p>¶ Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> I cannot tel what Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie mans Office is, neither doo I greatly force whether his Father be an <hi>Italian, Spaniard</hi> or <hi>Frenchman,</hi> but if he be the ſame in <hi>Latin</hi> that ſeruice is in Engliſh: I am ſure that both in <hi>Latin, French, Spanish</hi> and Engliſh hée ſtinketh when he is to frely offered, and that (I am very ſure) did <hi>Aeſop</hi> mean in his Fable of the Sowe great with pig vnto whome (ſaith hée) there came a For who alleadging vnto her his great ſkil in the art of a Midwife profferd her his ſeruice toward her deliuerance, vnto whome ſhée anſwered, that the greateſt and beſt ſeruice that hée could doo vnto her, was to kéep him far inough from her, which ſhee alſo prayed him to doo, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may gather what the <hi>Authors</hi> opinion was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this voluntary offer of ſeruice and yet hée dooth not alleage that the For offered any money, I ſuppoſe becauſe hée had no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to offer. But <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus</hi> offered money in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Acts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19011:15"/> Apoſtles, and what the holy Ghoſt thought therof: you may there vnderſtand, Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſt this is a colde reaſon and no Argument, to ſay that a mans earneſt deſire to haue an Office argueth his deſire of priuate gaine &amp; proffit, and ſo for his great deſire to doo good: condemne him of euil without proof therof. Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> I doo not ſo barely reaſon neither ſo nakedly as you haue alleaged if you did mée right in repetition of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not intercepting the ſame nor ſeuering the partes ther of as you haue doon, and ſo haue anſwered the firſt part by it ſelf which is the weakeſt and haue ſaid nothing to the ſecond part which is their great purchaſe and the ſtrength &amp; effect of the firſt, for my Argument taken, wholly togither is thus much to ſay, that their great deſire to haue the Offices, and their great purchaſe of Lands and liuing following the ſame, ſheweth that from the beginning there was ment nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght els but priuate pouching, for euer the act that is laſt in exception: is the firſt in Imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all mens dooings this is moſte aſſured. Neighbour (quoth our Hoaſt) this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of yours which you holde ſo forcible is of no force at all, whither the parties therof be conſidered iointly or ſeuerally, neither dooth this great deſire to be in Office, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great purchaſe enſuing the ſame in any wiſe diſprooue my firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſertion and maintenaunce of this great reuenues, fées and charges as you ſuppoſe, conſtruing and taking my ſaying to néer vnto the letter. For wheras I haue alleadged the Magiſtrates and Officers to be the Patrons and Fathers of the common welth, and theſe great reuenues a publick trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their hands to the vſes and intents abooue reherſed: yée alleadge againſt mée their great purchaſe of Lordſhips, Lands and Liuings as a repugnancie and diſpraiſe therof, which it is not but the greateſt &amp; ſtrongeſt confirmation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that I my ſelf haue alleaged, for although I haue made them receiuers yet haue I not charged them méerly as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers: but as Baylifs &amp; Gardens of truſt whoſe authoritie exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to improoue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefit of their Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries. But a better Improouement can there not be made: then by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of money which is tranſitory: into land which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent,
<pb facs="tcp:19011:16"/> namely béeing deliuered vnto them at their yéeres of diſcretion vpon the account of their ſaid Balifs or garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And euen as it fareth betwéen the Garden and his pupil, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Balifs and him to whoſe vſe he is put in truſt. So fareth it betwéen theſe Magiſtrates and Officers and the common welth as touching theſe receits.</p>
            <p>And therfore theſe purchaſes of lands &amp; poſſeſſions the beſt and moſte allowable diſcharge vpon their account that can poſſible be made vnto God, the greateſt and higheſt aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his honour and glory, the greateſt and moſte aſſured comfort and ſtay of his godly people and ſeruants vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the payment of the money from hand to hand had béen but a temporall and a ſhort reléef, for euery man hath not the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ne right vſe therof, to ſlipper is it and fugitiue.</p>
            <p>But theſe Lands in the hands of theſe Landlords are a ſtay perpetuall and permanent wherunto the godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſon is ſure of preferment and that for reaſon for why the Owners are ſuch in whome is no acceptaunce of Woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Fréendſhip, or of the greater offer, neither of other thig then vertue and godlynes, and therfore their rent muſt néeds be eaſie, for who ſhould rate it by out bidding when the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is no chapman neither dare preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him ſelf in the place for the godly perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dooth if no not vnto the wicked much leſſe vnto his godly Brother or Neighbour. This is no ſmall commendation of Vertue and godlynes and no ſmall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement therto, namely where a man may make as ſure &amp; a more ſure account of his Farme: then ſome other can make of their Inheritaunce and patrimony, which thing although it ſéem ſtraunge: yet is it commonly verified in the Farmers of ſuch Landlords. For wée ſée to often that diuerſe honeſt &amp; godly Men leaue their Inheritaunce vnto vngodly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftie Children who (falling into the hands of th' executor doo little while inioy the ſame. The cauſe wherof is for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they came to their lands before they came to their Wit, and béeing Owners waxed therby proude and in ſtate béeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no mans check and diſdaining all mens councel &amp; ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting God and them ſelues fall to follie and then (as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) <hi>Their table is made a ſnare to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19011:16"/> and the things which should haue been for their proffit, ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto them an occaſion of falling,</hi> So fearfull and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous is the ſinguler and ſole proprietie of great Lands and poſſeſſions, as that often times it not only bereaueth the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their right wit and Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but alſo through their pride, vnthriftines and prodigalitie it hazardeth the ſincere adminiſtration &amp; execution of lawes and Iuſtice, procuring partialite and fauour to vngodlynes and diſſolute liuing, whilſte they (whoſe dutie were to rebuke ſuch perſons and to reſtrain their libertie) had rather enter into their large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues and poſſeſſions and to take and vſe the opportunitie of their wickednes and retchleſnes as the méeteſt occaſion herto. But in theſe Farmers and in their poſteritie other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is and that for the reuerend and honourable regard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> betwéen them and their Land Lords at whoſe hands and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whoſe good wil and pleaſure they holde their liuings &amp; whoſe great liberalitie and benignitie chargeth them with no ſmall expectation aſwel of godly and honeſt conuerſation of life, as alſo of hoſpitalitie and charitable dealing with their Bretheren and Neighbours béeing by their meanes very wel enabled therunto. Theſe things (I ſay) are looked for at their hands and that by them whoſe expectation they dare not nor can not without great ſhame falſifie, which godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thriftines and liberalitie in them is of no ſmall force to mooue others therunto, and ſo mutuall looue and charitie che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed betwéen euery degrée, &amp; where theſe things are, God hath promiſed to bleſſe that houſe, Town, Cittie or Cuntry.</p>
            <p>It can hardly be ſpoken and much hardlyer written how greatly and how mightily this procureth and aduaunceth Learning, Godlynes and Vertue, how much it furthereth the deſire of contemplation and godly exerciſes of the minde, againſt which there is no Impediment nor hinderaunce ſo great as either the deſtitution or want of a competent liuing and maintenaunce, orels the dayly feare to de ſupplanted or diſapointed therof, and conſequently the thoughts and cares either to prouide for a competent liuing orels to maintaine and defend the ſame againſt the dayly Allarmes and aſſault<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Couetous and the vngodly againſt which the benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:19011:17"/> and goodnes of Owners and Land lords is the greateſt yea the only protection. Theſe are the effects and frutes of theſe purchaſes alleadged by you to be made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gains, fees and reuenues aforeſaid which doo far differ from the common purchaſing of other priuate perſons by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e (through your Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce orels of malice) you doo Iudge and meaſure theſe which are in nothing like nor comparable, as the effects and frutes therof will euidently declare, namely in the purchaſe of the Merchant, the Chapm a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Graſier, the Clothier and ſuch other like Artificer whatſoeuer, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of all which perſons no ſuch thing is hoped or looked for. Firſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they doo not ſuſtain any ſuch charge of expectation, neither is any reaſon that they ſhould, except a Shoomaker bying an Oxe hide for thrée ſhillings &amp; fourepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, might ſel ſhooes for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhillings a paire: for that would alter the caſe. Therfore as his calling is baſe and mean: ſo is his Iudgement as touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Vertue and the Felicitie and end of mans life, which hée Iudgeth to conſiſt in getting and hauing, for that hée ſéeeth men accounted and eſtéemed therafter, and other or farther. Contemplation hath hée very little or none. So that in his Oppinion hée ſpéedeth his matters wunderful wel if hée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn his Chaffer to his gain, &amp; the more and greater ſo much the better, be it land or leaſe of Farme or houſe, if he can ſel it again for double or treble that it coſt him or let it for thrée times the rent that hée payeth him ſelf for it. All this hée ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth honeſt gain and very wiſely handled, ſo that when hée hath any thing to let or ſet vp goeth the Drum &amp; as wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him the Deuil of hel, yea Belzabub him ſelf as the Godlyeſt perſon in England, yea as an Aungel of heauen, for godlynes, vertue or honeſtie is the laſt queſtion that hée wil aſke, onely Quid vultis mihi dare? Thus is the godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſure to be put back orels to take the thing to his vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, ſo that vpon the matter no queſtion or difference whither of them ſpéed, for the euil man is made a great deale wurſe, namely for that the greatnes of his rent ſtoppeth the mouth of him whoſe rebuke hée ſhould moſte feare &amp; whome hée would and ſhould moſte reuerence and regarde, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil hée be as wicked and as vngratious and corrupt as
<pb facs="tcp:19011:17"/> many others as hée can and dare for feare of the lawes. The godly perſon although hée gladly would doo good: yet wanteth hée power therto being ouer ſet with the greatnes of his re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo that in concluſion whether the good or euil may ſpéed: they are forced to deale hardly with the world wherby aryſeth lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle or no amitie, fréendſhip or charitable looue among men but euen all for the peny as among meer Straungers nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny zeale vnto God nor to doo any good for his ſake.</p>
            <p>By all theſe Arguments, it appéereth manifeſtly how much it were to be wiſhed and deſired at the hands of Almightie God, that only or chéefly ſuch were purchaſers &amp; Land lords whoſe very eſtates and callings and the manner of the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their gains wherwith they purchaſe doo charge them with a reuerend and fatherly regarde in letting and ſetting the ſame to the honor and glory of God who hath ſo mightily bleſſed them, yea ſo far abooue all that they euer could with out ſhame haue wiſhed or deſired, ſo heaping hot coles vpon their heds in their vnthankfulnes and dealing otherwiſe, which (as I haue alredy ſaid) is not or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt not ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bée hoped or looked for at their hands of bace and mean calling. And therfore Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and confeſſing the greatnes of their purchaſe: yet can yée not conclude againſt mée the proper or priuate receit or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of Charges, Fées &amp; reuenues aforeſaid neither will I graunt it vnto you, for the ſlaunderous and ſhamefull con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequence which it inferreth neceſſaryly as hath already béen duly prooued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce repeteth the Reaſons and Arguments of Simon and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by proof and experience demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratiſe as from the cauſe to the effect and that vpon his ovvne knovvledge. Cha. 10.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:18"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> yée haue made as your ſelf dooth ſuppoſe many ſtrong reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to aprooue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt aſeſſing and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now receiuig of eight pence or twelue pence for a ſhéet of paper, and other exceſſiue and vnreaſonable Fées and charges of ſutes as not only tollerable, iuſt and reaſonable: but alſo godly and moſte conducible vnto the common welth, and to the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous and good eſtate therof, namely for that theſe Fées &amp; charges were ment and yet are the puniſhment of vice and the rewarde of godlynes &amp; vertne. And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they were &amp; yet are ment a publike treaſure in the hands of the Receiuers therof, to all godly vſes, intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Wherunto I anſwered, alleadging the grrat purchaſe of Lands and Lordſhips by the Receiuers of the ſame as a thig repugnant and contrary to your Aſſertion, wherunto you haue replied that their great purchaſe is not only contrary to your firſt Aſſertion but a confirmation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>For you ſay that their purchaſe of lands is a prouiſion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out compariſon more aſſured and permanent then were or could haue béen the diſtribution of the money or any parte therof from hand to hand, and alſo that the effects and frute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof are moe and greater and doo ſtretch farther and more generally and vniuerſally doo procure the honor and glory of God, and the publique welth, peace and quietnes.</p>
            <p>To prooue that theſe things are ſo: you haue alleadged the honorable calling of the Magiſtrate and Officer, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great expectation that hée ſuſteineth bothe before God and Men, &amp; alſo the reuerend oppinion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wée are bound to haue of him.</p>
            <p>Yée haue alſo alleadged that the firſt cauſes of all theſe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at gains and proffits are ſuch as of dutie hée is bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and not to proſecute, namely for that they are vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, wickednes and all kinde of vice, by the gain wherof (ſay you) no honeſt nor godly perſon can without great ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thriue and wax rich, much leſſe the Magiſtrate and Officer vpon whoſe great expectation héerin you doo ſo greatly inſiſt.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (quoth hée) all theſe are goodly and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo godly reaſons and doo very wel prooue how things either
<pb facs="tcp:19011:18"/> haue béen orels how things ought to be.</p>
            <p>But that they are ſo preſently: theſe are either no prooues at all or very ſmall and ſo your argument gathered and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from <hi>poſſe</hi> to <hi>eſſe</hi> as I haue ſaid already, and as I wil further prooue by Arguments gathered from the cauſe vnto the effect and from the effect vnto the cauſe euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſame that you haue alleadged, tying them togither in the ſame maner and fourme as your ſelf haue alleadged them.</p>
            <p>Firſt you ſay that the originall cauſe of theſe grreat gains, Fées and reuenues was the hate that the firſt Aſſeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of bare vnto vngodlynes, wickednes and all kinde of vice, the fauour and good affection which they bare vnto Vertue, and godlynes, and therin they ment the puniſhment of the one and the preferment and aduauncment of the other, and ſo you conclude lewdnes, vnthriftines and vngodlynes to haue béen and yet ſtil to be the firſt cauſe of theſe great gains, Fées and reuenues, and theſe great Fées and reuenues their effect, the effect of theſe fées, proffits and reuenues yée haue alleadged or rather I my ſelf haue alleadged, and you haue confeſſed and iuſtified to be the great perquiſition and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Lordſhips, lands and poſſeſſions by the Magiſtrates and Officers Receiuors of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The effect of their great purchaſe is by you aleadged to be a prouiſion, a ſtay of liuing and patrymony for the Godly and honeſt People of the common welth, and for their aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, peace and quietnes. The effect of ſo good a prouiſion for the Godly: you haue alleadged to be the increaſe of them, and the decreaſe of the wicked, vnthriftie and vngodly, the effect of the increaſe of godly people you haue alleadged to be mutuall looue &amp; charitie and all good affection bothe towards God and alſo one to an other, the effect wherof you haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged to be the manifolde bleſſings of God according to the ſaying of the Prophet in the hundred thrée &amp; thirtie <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue you argued from the firſt cauſes producing their effects, and from thoſe effects as from cauſes of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffects very orderly and very probablie but not neceſſarilye as I haue alreadye alleadged, and as I dout not héerafter
<pb facs="tcp:19011:19"/> I ſhall prooue vnto you ſo directly and ſo euidently that you ſhall either confeſſe your owne prooues fallible and falls: or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els you muſt and ſhal ſay that cauſes produce no effects orels clean contrary effects, which is to reuerſe and to ouerthrow the order of Nature and all the law and rule of reaſon as to ſay there can be a Father or a Mother without a Sonne or a Daughter or that betwéen a man or a woman there ſhould be begotten a dogge or a cat. And for proof héerof I wil allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge bothe reaſon as ſtrong as you haue alleaged any: and alſo myne owne experience which I my ſelf haue déerly bought and paid for. I pray you Neighbour let mée hear that (quoth our Hoaſt.)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce Plovvmans firſt tale for that purpoſe vvhere hee sbevveth hovv his Neighbour and hee vvent to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern and to the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing Schoole and vvhat hapned there. Cha. 11.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T my béeing in London this laſt terme (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> it fortuned one after noone hauing lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing to doo, as God knoweth what I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlenes and vngodlynes commeth of our idle wayting and attending vpon our dayes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as they tearm them, when in the mean time wée run vp and down in the ſtréets, and if happily wée méet with any Fréend or acquantaunce it is holden great humanitie to off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er him the curteſie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is as much to ſay to haue him to the Tauern &amp; there to ſit bibbing vntil neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſcant finde the way foorth again. So as I was about to tel you, one day amongſt all others wee met a company of Neighbours and Fréends togither in Poules ſix in number all Cuntrie men and Neighbours, ſaue one that was a Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doner a Neighbour borne of ours, who was our Leader to many a good place dout you not, ſo on Gods name néeds wée muſt to the Tauern, and ſo wée went to the Tauern, there faſt by, wherby that time wée ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e foorth again: our heds were better laden with heare then with Wit, ſo on Gods name
<pb facs="tcp:19011:19"/> when our heds were wel fraughted: wée muſt néeds go to ſee ſome pleaſures of the Cittie that were ſtraunge and noueltie vnto vs of the Cuntrie, and ſo on Gods name wée went into a dauncing Schoole not very far thence, now was there one man of our Company that was as deaf as a doore naile.</p>
            <p>¶ When wée weare come into the Schoole: the Muſitions were playing and one dauncing of a Galiard, and euen at our entring hée was beginning a trick as I remember of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téens or ſeuentéens, I doo not very wel reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber but wunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hée leaped, flung and took on, which the deaf man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and not hearing any noyſe of the Muſick, thought verily that hée had béen ſtark mad and out of his wit, and of pure pittie and compaſſion ran to him and caught him in his armes and held him hard and faſt. The Dauncer not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his good meaning and taking it to the wurſt, and hauing a Dagger drew it out and ſmot the man a great blowe vpon the hed, and brake his hed very ſore.</p>
            <p>The man ſore mooued and gréeued therwithall, and bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man of great ſtrength: threw him from him with all his ſtrength among the Muſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and bée lighting vpon one of the greateſt and faireſt Vialles, brake it all in péeces.</p>
            <p>Therwithall vp ſtart the Muſitions for him and wée for to help the other béeing our Fréends and Neighbours, and then went out Daggers, vp went Pantotles, all the reſt of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in the the throng w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re all to trodden and broken, and but that Neighbours hearing the noiſe &amp; buſtling came in and parted vs: ſurely ſome of vs had béen in grea daunger to haue béen ſlain.</p>
            <p>I loſt my Cloke and had my hed broken and ſo had thrée of my Neighbours moe, and hardly the Muſitions and their part takers went not ſcotfrée. But ſhortly to end &amp; come to my purpoſe: you ſhall heare what followed.</p>
            <p>Firſt and formoſte wée were all arreſted and committed to Priſon for a fraie and bloodſhed, where I think you may make no queſtion if it coſt vs any thing before wée gat out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But hauing paid our Fées there, and thinking veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the wurſt had béen paſt: euen at our comming foorth from thence wée were all newly arreſted by latitates and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
<pb facs="tcp:19011:20"/> vntil wée had put in Suretiee to appéere at the day of the return of the writ in the Kingsbench. So wée laid our purſes togither and went to a woorſhipful and learned Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer that had béen of our councel aforetime, and ſhewed him the declarations that were againſt vs, wherof the firſt was at the ſute of the Owner of the ſcoole, wherin hée alleadged that with force and armes wée had entred into his houſe and beaten, wounded and euil intreated his Seruants, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof hée had loſt their ſeruice by the ſpace of right dayes, to his hinderaunce and damage ſixpound, and alſo then and there thrée Inſtruments of Muſick commonly called Vialls did ſpoile and break to his loſſe and hinderaunce ſixpound.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, euery of his Seruants the parties the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſeuearlly declared againſt vs all iointly of an aſſault and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery made vpon them, and that wée had beaten, wounded &amp; euil intreated them to their ſeuerall damages fortipence, the Dauncer himſelf declared ſeuerally againſt the deaf man for aſſaults and battery, vpon all which matters wée prayed his councel and aduiſe, his anſwere was ſhortly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the law was againſt vs in all &amp; euery of our caſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hée gaue vs the cauſes &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as I ſhall reherſe vnto you.</p>
            <p>To the firſt point of the firſt delaration for forcible entrye wée praied his reaſon, how or by what reaſon our entrie mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be ſaid forciblo ſéeing the doores were open, and if they had béen ſhut our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in was but to hear &amp; ſée, &amp; our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning not hurtful to any man. His anſwere therunto was that a mans meaning that commeth into my houſe ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued and taken to haue béen ſuch from the beginning as is his act there doon after he is entred, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalbe taken for his meaning &amp; the declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, namely where hée entreth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſpeciall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the party, &amp; becauſe (ſaith hée) that after your entry into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> houſe yée did there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a force &amp; an vnlawful act: therfore your firſt entry &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the houſe ſhalbe déemed &amp; iudged vnlawful &amp; forci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. Then wée aſked how or by what reaſon our act could be ſaid vnlawful which was but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> taking of a man in his arme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of very goodwill to ſtay him thinking that he had béen mad &amp; out of his wit and might haue miſcheiued him ſelf. His aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers
<pb facs="tcp:19011:20"/> therunto was that therin the act was not lawful nor iuſticiable but a Treſpaſſers although no farther harme had enſued therupon, which yet (by your confeſſion) there did, for to ſpeak generally: it is not lawful to imbrace or ſtrain any man againſt his wil, for if him liſt to take it to the wurſt (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if there enſue any euil vnto the partie therby) it ſhal not help the party to ſay that hée ment him good or at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> leaſt no euil therby, for although that in felony the intent doo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the fact it is not ſo in Treſpaſſers wherfore your act was not lawful nor Iuſticiable except yée had béen Officers or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yée had come in &amp; found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dooing ſome felonious or vnlawful act, by means wherof yée had had ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to haue laid yourha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for euery man is an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficer for peace ſake &amp; for the preſeruacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, &amp; then (quoth hée) your caſe had béen otherwiſe, vnto this wée aunſwered that our act in all reaſon ſéemed more lawful and tollerable then theirs, for that in their exerciſe there is little good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or none at all, nor better end or purpoſe then to induc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch euil and vnhappy euents and conſequents as hapned in this caſe of ours, and that therfore their cauſe ought not to haue fauour againſt vs as if wée had hindred or interrupted their honeſt or lawful exerciſe in any godlynes or in any thig tending vnto vertue, to the glory of God or to the proffit of the common welth. His aunſwere vnto that was that we are not to diſpute of that which the reuerend and honorable Magiſtrates haue eſtabliſhed yea &amp; holden in no ſmall repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it falleth for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Magiſtrates, Rulers &amp; Officers to beare with them in all incidents &amp; caſualties otherwiſe ſhould they diſalowe their owne Acts and be contrary vnto them ſelues, which were inconuenient. Then wée demannded of him why for the firſt Viall that was broken: the Maiſter ſhould not bring the action againſt the Dauncer who in very déed was the breaker therof, and not the other man. His aunſwer therunto was that in very déed wée were bothe Treſpaſſers vnto him alike, &amp; he at his libertie &amp; election to take his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy aginſt vs bothe or againſt any of vs for (quoth hée) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſer were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> materiall cauſe yet was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other man y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe therof, asfor proof, if a carter wilfully driue his cart ouer
<pb facs="tcp:19011:21"/> a man, woman or Childe, bothe the cart, the horſes, and the Carter are guiltie of the fact wherof the deaf man is not excuſable neither can plead not guiltie to the fact, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée was the firſt and chéef efficient cauſe, therupon wée mooued vnto him this queſtion, why the Muſitions them ſelues ſhould not be ſaid to be the firſt efficient cauſe ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without their noiſe the Dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer would not ſo haue fared nor taken on, neither the deaf man haue taken him for a madde man, as bothe you and wée would haue doon if wée had béen in his caſe, and had heard no more then hée heard.</p>
            <p>Vnto that his anſwere was, that whatſoeuer it ſéemed vnto him or vnto vs, it is (quoth hée) at your peril, and at all mens perils els that reſorte &amp; haunt to ſuch places to put on all our Sences, wits and vnderſtandings, and alſo to deſire God to giue them wiſdome and his grace to Iudge wiſely &amp; wel to digeſt ſuch things as they heare and ſée therin, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wée be not ſnared in euil thorugh ignorant appetite of our ſences vnto our hinderaunces more then wée our ſelues are able of our ſelues to Iudge or think, for (ſaith hée) ſéeing wée are not able, neither is our authoritie to blame or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the places; neither to diſalowe the things there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, which were to derogate from the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Yet if wée haue ſo much grace of God as to be Magiſtrates vnto our ſelues and in ſuch caſes to blame and reprooue our ſelues, and our owne ſences, and inordinat deſires, either in due time before wée are fallen, orels in ſome reaſonable time, and with our reaſonable loſſe and hinderaunce it may ſuffice for anſwere vnto vs by them vnto whome otherwiſe wée muſt créep and pray our redreſſe neither able to craue it at their hands without an inconuenience aforeſaid, which is condemn and diſalowe the things by them ſelues allowed and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Wée aſked him what reaſon there was that wée ſhould be charged in ſeuerall actions and vnto ſeuerall Perſons, for one treſpaſſe, as namely vnto the Maiſter and alſo to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. His anſwere thervnto was that the Maiſter hath a ſpeciall intereſt in his ſeruant for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proffit hée is to receiue by his ſeruice for which ſeruice hée is to recouer &amp; not for the
<pb facs="tcp:19011:21"/> hurt doon vnto the perſon for the partie him ſelf recouereth for that. To be ſhort, his reſolution was that for all our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rmes and loſſe that wée had gotten: wée weare ſo far from all hope of redreſſe or amends, that wée were in the wurſe caſe in our defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; very like to yéeld amends by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of law. And thus you ſée (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> how poore guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe &amp; ſimple men in a far honeſter cauſe are put to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wurſer end. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoaſt) as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, be as bée may. But truely Neighbour you had but euil ſucceſſe in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſée pleaſure and to heare Muſick, and yet truſt mée if yée wil, I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you ſped a great deale better then a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſpéed in ſuch like places, who think neuertheleſſe them ſelues to haue ſped there wel, and come away right wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, which in very déed is the only cauſe why in my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie they ſpéed wurſe then you, for why you are hurt and féel it, but they are hurt but haue no féeling therof vntil their hurt be paſt all cure, for a man is neuer ſo daungerouſly ſick or ſore as when hée hath loſt the ſence and féeling of the ſore or of the ſicknes. So fareth it in ſuch perſons as theſe, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they féel no euil that they contract, and yet in ſuch places, yet doo they carry thence with them the ſéeds and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall cauſes of great Infortunes as the woful and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end of many a good mans Childe hath witneſſed dayly, dooth &amp; wil. But truely Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoaſt) you are waxen more then half a Lawyer by theſe meanes.</p>
            <p>Nay ſoft (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> I haue an other matter to tel you and that almoſte as ſtraunge as this, and that chaunced to my ſelf in a miſchaunce about a foure yéeres paſt, I pray yée let vs heare it quoth our Hoaſt, marry quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> thus it hapned, A Fréend of mine would néeds giue mée my din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at an Ordinary table where wée fared very daintily, but I promiſe you for myne owne parte I haue thought my ſelf better at eaſe many a time &amp; oft with bread &amp; chéeſe in other Company. So Sir in the name of God when dinner was doon: in ſtéed of grace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dice they went on euery ſide vpon proper ſquare tables fit I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe, &amp; there to the hazard they go xx. s. xl, s. v. l. vi. l. a caſt, I ſtood by and beheld. Anon there came a Straunger a plain homely fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe of the Cuntrye much like my ſelf and hée ſéeing ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:19011:22"/> ſums of money vpon the boorde, and the dice trotting to &amp; fro, and that now one ſnatched a heap and now another ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an heap, and ther withall ſuch deuout ſwearing, hée came is mée and rowning mée in the eare, aſked mée whoſe weare all thoſe heaps of money that weare laid foorth, mary (quoth I) his that can get them, get them (quoth hée) how? Marry (quoth I) by hazard, ſay you ſo (quoth hée) claime they no farther propertie in their money but by hazard whether them ſelues ſhall haue their money or an other man? no veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (quoth I.) What are thoſe white things full of black ſpots that are ſo chaced to and fro? Thoſe (quoth I) are called dice vpon whome ſtandeth the hazard, &amp; ther withall my Fréend and I hauing dined and diſpatched: went our way foorth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Temple, and before wée had gon ſo farre as a man might ſhoot a Bird bolte: there aroſe an outery behinde vs, ſtop the théef, ſtop the théef, and ther withall I looked behinde mée: and loe the fellowe of whome I tolde you, came running with bothe his hands ful of money and after him ran the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Ordinary and thrée or foure of his ſeruants as faſt as euer they could run with hue &amp; cry, wée turned not back neither made vs to doo therin. So they followed him vntill they came as farre as Saint Dunſtanes Church, and there the fellowe béeing out of breath, turned again and catching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Maiſter of the dicing houſe in his armes: cryed I haue him I haue him, this is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> théef (quoth hée) Now was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at that a man could not know which was which vntil at the laſt the Officers came and took them bothe and knowing the Maiſter of the dicing houſe: aſked him what the matter was.</p>
            <p>Mary (quoth hée) this Villain Théef hath robbed diuers Men of Woorſhip my Gueſts of great ſummes of money and I haue followed him for hée ded vpon the ſelony. And there-hée had ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed mée in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany &amp; bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay holde vpon mée for this knaue (quoth hée) gaue him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel &amp; is as falſe théef as hée: There was no more to ſay, I was &amp; laid holde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and bothe hée and I caried before a Iuſticer of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ace the Fellowe and I, my Fréend would not leaue mée but went with mée to ſée and heare the end. So Sir, when wée were come before the Iuſticer: hée laid fore to the Fellowes
<pb facs="tcp:19011:22"/> charge that hée had broken his houſe forciblie and burglarlie and had feloniouſly robbed foure Gentlemen of woorſhip his Gueſts of diuers ſummes of money feloniouſly and againſt the Quéens lawes and peace. Sirra (quoth the Iuſtice) what ſaiſt thou to this? Sir quoth the fellowe I beſéech you to ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my good Fréend and Maiſter and let mée haue but law &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at your hands, I truſt it appéereth vnto your diſcretion (quoth hée) that this matter alleadged againſt mée is not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficient to put mée to anſwere therunto. Firſt for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible entrie into his houſe and burglarye ſuppoſed: I ſay his houſe was open, and daily is and to long hath béen and vnto to many if it pleaſed God and the Magiſtrate ſuch as your Woorſhip is, for I vndertake hée that hath any thing to loſe and caſt away: néed neither break doore nor wall to leaue it behinde him there, and ſomuch for mine anſwere vnto that part. As to the money ſuppoſed to be ſtolne: hée declareth no certaintie therof, neither conueieth to him ſelf any property therin, and ſo no felony of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing wherto no man claimeth propertie, very true it is (quoth hée) that I came into his houſe and ſéeing a company ſtanding about a ſquare Table &amp; diuers greet heaps of money laid foorth therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I aſked this honeſt man that was a ſtander by meaning (mée) what was ment therby, and alſo by two white ſquare things full of black ſpots that were chaſed to and fro vpon the boord, hée anſwered mée that they were playing at the dice, for that is quoth hée the name of thoſe ſquare bones, and ſaid farther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the name of their game was hazard. When, I had heard him ſay ſo: I conſidered with my ſelf that there might be good to be doon for mée among them, for hauing wel marked their order: I found them the moſte indifferent People to gain by that euer I met withall in my life, for I perceiued that hée that laide the money downe: the reſt meant that hée ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld neuer take it vp again, and for his part hée ment aſwell vnto them and that all this ſtood in the fauour of hazard, and ſo often time it chaunced accordingly, to wit that the box bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: caught a ſhare and by no other nor better title then mée thought my ſelf to haue, for mée thought I was as indifferent to euery of them as was the box or as any of
<pb facs="tcp:19011:23"/> them was to oſver, for I verily thought and yet doo that if nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of them euer fingered that laid down either had his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire againſt other, moreouer quoth hée, when I beheld ſuch lewde and ſhameful miſpending of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, ſuch horrible ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and blaſpheming &amp; knew not where neither vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to complain for reformation therof &amp; thought in Conſcience I ought not to ſuffer it as farfoorth as were in my might, &amp; I ſaw no way ſo likely to redreſſe it as to take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe which I perceiued was the money: I thought that bothe by law and good Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I might doo it and ought alſo, and in this deliberation I awaited my time and ſnatched vp al that I could lay holde vpon and came my way, wherupon I pray your diſcretion and whether this be fellony wherin there is title or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt cullour of title. A Sirra quoth the Iuſticer, you are a cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning théef indéed, it is time to look to ſuch knaues as you are. Sir quoth the poore fellowe, I beſéech you be good to me, I am a poore man and I truſt, ſauing againſt them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſt the money the money is mine againſt all men and as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me: let me anſwere. And as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that honeſt man quoth hée, by me, I neuer delt with him nor neuer ſaw him before, to be ſhort the Fellowe was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Newgate, and I was fain to finde ſuretie by recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaunce to appéer at the next ſeſſions there to make anſwer to ſuch mater as ſhould then and there be laid to my charge, and that coſt mée fiue ſhillings and this was all that I got by hauing my dinner giuen mée.</p>
            <p>And what ſaid your Lawyer to you for this ſaid our Hoaſt, what comfort dooth hée giue you of a mends againſt the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that thus miſuſed you, truely (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> hée vtterly diſcourageth mée to ſtur or meddle farther therin, and all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame reaſons that hée made before orels the very like in effect, Truely Neighbour quoth our Hoaſt, that Lawyer was no Counceller neither for your purpoſe and much leſſe for his owne. Why ſo Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce?)</hi> marry quoth our Hoaſt, for there is no courage in him, neither hath he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to help him ſelf, &amp; to keep you in dooi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he giueth ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel to peace &amp; quietnes, vnto ſuch fellowes as you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> would gladly cut hi out woork if him ſelf were not his owne hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Nay ſurely Neighbour ꝙ <hi>Pierce,</hi> what councel
<pb facs="tcp:19011:23"/> ſoeuer he had giuen me therin, or what councel he or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them all ſhall héerafter giue me in ſuch matters: I am taught alredy though to my coſt, while I liue to looue peare &amp; enſue it, &amp; to looue mine owne houſe, my honeſt labour &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel and chéefly &amp; abooue all other things to ſerue God, wherin I finde the only ſtay and comfort of mans life to reſt, &amp; that when all is ſought and tried: there is none other rule ne le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel wel and ſurely to guyde &amp; order our affaires &amp; dooings.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>The application of Pierces tale by the Hoſte, that the great charges of the Lavv is profitable to the common vvelth, and a repreſſing of vice and ſinne. Chap. 13.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ha, very wel ſaid then (quoth our Hoſte) I am glad that yet at the laſt ye are come to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> point whereunto I haue all this while laboured to bring you, which is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that theſe great and exceſſiue charges and expences haue refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and changed you from an vngodly &amp; troubleſome man: to a godly, wiſe and prudent man, able to giue councell not only priuatly and to your owne fréends and family: but alſo to beare office and authoritie in your Pariſh, yea in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole Shire where we bothe dwel, ſo that I hope from hencefoorth we ſhall haue great ſtore of you, and that of the greatnes of ſuch fées and charges of ſutes in Law, and of the firſt Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſors and the now receiuers therof ye are vtterly concluded &amp; eſtopped to ſpeak or think ſaue in all honor &amp; reuerence, Doo you think ſo Neighbour (quoth he?) Yea verily quothe he, for you haue confeſſed all this your reformation &amp; amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue comen thence, &amp; look what effect it hath wrought in you: ye are of charitie bound to think that it hath wrought, woorketh &amp; wil woork in a number moe then you, &amp; the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that you haue or rather think that haue departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: is in their hands who are treaſurers therof, as I haue alleaged towards the good and godly vſes, intents &amp; purpoſes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> may or ſhall ariſe héerafter in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon benefit, to wit, ſeruice of the whole common welth, wherin your parte is as far foorth as theirs. Doo ye call this a mending Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> quoth <hi>Peirce?</hi> In very déed quoth he, I muſt néeds confeſſe, that theſe great and exceſſiue Charges and large Expences haue
<pb facs="tcp:19011:24"/> rebuked me, haue chaſtiſed and amended me, but to ſay that I think or iudge it thank woorthy vnto them that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued my money: I ſay the Deuill kiſſe his arſe that ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth me or any fréend of mine, for verily ſuch amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my iudgement, deſerueth aſmuch and the very like thanks as did the Wife, who gaue her huſband two ſtrong poyſons, meaning to ſpéed him in déed, but the poyſons bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of contrary natures: wrought one vppon an other, and deſtroyed either others force, wherby the man béeing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled for a ſeaſon, yet béeing driuen into a lax by their extremetie: auoyded them bothe and with them much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſo that where before he was a very corrupt body: he was by their clenſings the better xx. yéeres after. Thus ſhe did him good by accident, but far from her intent or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and vtterly againſt her will. And ſurely they that take ſo exceſſiuely of me and of others our money, &amp; by that kinds of puniſhment amend and refourme vs: I holde them woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as much thank therfore as was this Wife at her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands hand for his amendment which was wrought by her meane. For I dare ſafely vndertake, that for our affliction and puniſhment, or for the diſhonor of God and other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines that dependeth therupon: they are as ſorowfull as was the pariſh Clark of a Town that was ſore viſited with the Plague, who ſaid vnto his wife vpon a day. Wife (quoth he) if there come two corpſes to day: we will haue a ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mutton and a quart of Sack to ſupper, &amp; if there come but one: we will haue a ſhoulder of Mutton and but a pinte of Sack. Content huſband (quoth ſhe). And veryly I think that as hartily as this good man &amp; his Wife prayed for their recouery that were viſited: ſo hartily pray theſe for peace, quietnes and the honor and ſeruice of God, and the Godly &amp; charitable dealing and liuing of their Neighbours and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Pierce prooueth that the ſufferaunce of vvickednes and vngodlines: increaſeth their gayne vvho are and should be the rebukers and punishers therof, and that to be the cauſe of great iniuſtice &amp; vnrightuouſnes. Chap. 14.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:24"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) I pray you let me further vnderſtand what yée doo meane by this Hiſtory, for it ſhould ſéeme y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ye haue alleadged it againſt me, not with ſtanding that it maketh for me by the wun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effect which you your ſelf are forced to confeſſe, that it hath wrought vpon you. I knowe what I haue confeſſed Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> and alſo in what maner I haue confeſſed it, far enough from your purpoſe or any confirmation therof. And where in maintenance of theſe great fées and reuenues you haue alleaged that they are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, &amp; alſo how many and how good and godly are the'ffects and frutes therof: without proofe made of them or of any one of them, either by your owne experience or by other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry demonſtration. There in proofe of the contrary to wit, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they are proper and priuate, and therfore exceſſiue and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable which is my aſſertion, I haue brought you this proofe of mine owne experience, wherby I haue ſufficiently ſhewed that the firſt cauſes of all theſe great gaines and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are proſecuted as I haue affirmed and not perſecuted as you pretend. For I haue partely ſhewed you héere what lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue &amp; libertie the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people namely youth hath to followe their owne luſt and deſire, in all want<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnes and diſſolution of life. For further proofe wherof: I call to witneſſe the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aters, Courtaines, Heauing houſes, Kiſſing boothes, Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alleyes and ſuch places where the time is ſo ſhamefully miſpent, namely the Sabaoth dayes vnto the great diſhonor of God, and the corruption and vtter deſtruction of youth. All which (I ſay) are either the cauſes or the effects of theſe great gaynes and reuenues, or els bothe cauſes and effects interchaungeably. For I dare vndertake that if either theſe gaynes and profits were publique as you pretend, or els if there were as great gayn and profit to the Magiſtrates and Officers, in the godly liues and honeſt conuerſation of the common people as there is in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary: theſe harbours of vngodlines &amp; miſnurture, would haue leſſe fauour and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce then they haue, and godlines, Sobrietie and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb facs="tcp:19011:25"/> of liues &amp; maners: would be in greater eſtimation then they are, and the honor and glory of God more aduaunced therby. But alas that the honor and glory of God and the vaine glory, pomp and maieſtie of man cannot ſtand togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; that one of them muſt néeds fall in the others exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for certainly the more libertie vnto wickednes &amp; ſinne, and the more falling from God through the ſame: and the more humbly complainings vnto your good Lordſhips, and vnto your good Woorſhips. The more Recognances for the peace and good a bearing, aſwell by the Godly as by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, the one inuading and the other defending: the more praying, paying, waiting, attending, dowking, crowding, &amp; courteſying, procuring of fréendſhip by meanes, bribing of his flatterer, &amp; bribing of her flatterer, this driueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great welth and abundance into fewe mens hands. For where the vngodly through miſgouerment is fallen into daunger of the Law, what will he not giue to redéeme his life or his infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye? yea euen vnto them who were the firſt cauſes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of his fall into ſuch folly and miſchaunce through li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and not reſtraint of the contempt of God, his Lawes, and ſeruice, which he will not fayle to meaſure and fully to reward vnto all libertines, contemners and deſpiſers of his maieſtie and will, giuen then ouer into a reprobate minde, from vice vnto vice, vntill he hath fully brought him to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught. So dangerous and fearful a thing is libertie and not reſtraint of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of euill, which although they appéer not ſuch at the firſt: yet when they are come to their ripenes and haue brought foorth their increaſe to wit, Fellonyes, Thefts, Man ſlaughter, Murder and ſuch like: there is not ſo ignorant a perſon that will not ſay, the man or woman was neuer like to come to better end, namely for his euil and diſſolute life in the beginning.</p>
            <p>This libertie is in the hands of Magiſtrates and Officers to bid or to forbid, euen after as they will prefer the honor and glory of God, or els their owne welth, pomp and vayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory. And therfore how hartily were it to be deſired at the hands of GOD, that ſuch as are Magiſtrates and Officers:
<pb facs="tcp:19011:25"/> ſhould not be couetuoꝰ, orels ſuch as are couetoꝰ ſhould not be Magiſtrates, for héerof lethro did warne <hi>Moyſes</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> xviy. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> talking w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; choiſe of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates &amp; Officers, &amp; bad him chooſe ſuch as hated couetiſe, &amp; ſpake of no other vice. The cauſe wherof is apparant, to wit leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wickednes &amp; vngodlynes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people came to be valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble let and ſet, re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; farmed, bought &amp; ſolde, for what other thing is valuing, letting &amp; ſetting, re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, buying &amp; ſelling of offices whoſe value is more or leſſe accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of the people &amp; their diſhonournig of God therby. And where you maintain theſe great gains by their godly &amp; woorthy effects, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt wherof you alleadge to be their great purchaſe of Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Lands &amp; poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; the effect therof you alleadge to be a prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; patrimony for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good &amp; godly, the effect wherof yée ſay is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> increaſe of them, &amp; the decreaſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, the effect wherof you ſay is godlynes, vnanimitie, looue, charitie &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie one towards an other. And laſt of all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> effect therof be the manifolde graces &amp; bleſſings of God, promiſed by God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Pſalmes</hi> to the houſe, town, Cittie or Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie where theſe things are. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt cauſe to his effect I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theſe great gains are cauſe of great purchaſe, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purchaſe to his effects yée ſhew not how it is: but how it ought to be, for in ſtéed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effects wherof you haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſée ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gay houſes ful of gay chineis, coſtly ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quetig houſes, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leryes, bowling Alleis, ſtraunge toies of point deuiſe &amp; woork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, but within I finde no man dwellig ſaue Pride, who hath chaſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hoſpitalitie &amp; charitie, &amp; as for other prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the godly haue at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in any of their purchaſes: I ſée none but euen who will giue moſte, &amp; can make migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt fréends, &amp; who thoſe are in our daies: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly, vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful &amp; vncharitable dealing ſo vniuerſally, doo plainly declare.</p>
            <p>The people ſo euil giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe yung &amp; olde, ſo vngodly in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo vnciuil, yea ſo rude &amp; barbaroꝰ in manners, wherin me thinketh they haue preuailed &amp; increaſed more &amp; more all after as theſe office? haue waxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ful &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greater. And therfore your diſtincton betwéen the in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Chapma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer (ſauing his probabilitie) vain &amp; ridiculoꝰ to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purpoſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:26"/>
            <p>Therfore Neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> your reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are weak, and to maintaine the greatnes of their fées vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Abide Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoſte, giue me leaue to anſwere you vnto theſe matters, and firſt becauſe that in very déed probable reaſon giueth place to neceſſary proof and demonſtration, wherin ye ſuppoſe that ye haue gon beyond me, becauſe that againſt my bare and naked reaſons as you terme them, ye haue alleaged authoritie, and that of your owne experience: I will anſwere you with the like, &amp; that of mine owne experience alſo, and more direct vnto my mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any of yours, which are indéed indirect and ſtand in different, and I will prooue that the Magiſtrate and Officer in the beginning was and yet is ſuch as I haue alleaged, and alſo the firſt aſſeſſing of the ſaid fées and reuenues, and their great vtilitie and neceſſitie, namely for the vſes, intents and purpoſes aforeſaid. For proofe wherof I will rehearſe vnto you a matter which I my ſelf did bothe heare and ſée.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>The Hoſte maintaineth the contrary, and for diſproofe therof, and for the proofe of his aſſertion: alleadgeth the purchaſe of a certain vvelthie Officer tovvards the Lavv. Chap. 15.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout two yéeres agon it was my fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be beyond London in <hi>Kent,</hi> at the houſe of a woorſhipfull Officer towards the Law, who not paſt a Moneth before my comming thither: had purchaſed a Lordſhip, wherin were diuers good Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; their leaſes to expire at Michel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas then to come twelue Moneths. It came to paſſe one day of my béeing there: thither came a rich man dwelling not very far thence, whoſe ſute was to this Gentleman to take one of his ſaid Farmes in reuertion, and comming to him thus he began. Sir quoth he, I vnderſtand ye haue bought ſuch a Lordſhip, God giue ye ioy therof. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true it is (ꝙ he.) Sir quoth this rich man, I pray you let me be your tenaunt of ſuch a Farm, giuing more then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her man wil giue for a fine. The rent of the Farm was v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:26"/>
            <p>What wil ye giue me for a leaſe for xxi. yéeres quoth this Gentleman? Sir quoth he, I wil giue ye an C. l. &amp; vnto our Miſtreſſe a Veluet gown, &amp; xx. Angels to buy her pinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. You haue bidden like a chapman ſaid the Gentleman, giue me leaue to be aduiſed vnto Munday next ſaid he, and then I ſhall giue you an anſwere héerin, ſo cauſing him to tary dinner he let him depart, and this was vpon a Thurſday.</p>
            <p>The next day béeing Friday: this Gentleman ſent for the Farmer of the ſame péece of land, who came thither, &amp; with him thrée hanſome young men his ſonnes. So when he was by the Landlords commaundement brought before him: he aſked him of what age he was. He anſwered lxxv. yéeres. He aſked him how long he had dwelled in that Farm. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he had dwelt there all his life for he was borne in it and his father before him. You knowe quoth the Gentleman that I am now become your Landlord. I knowe it very wel quoth he, and I beſéech you of your fauour. What will you giue for a new leaſe of xxi yéeres quoth the Gentleman? for you knowe your olde leaſe is néer an end. Sir quoth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poore man, let me giue you reaſon, only that I may be able to dooe my Prince and your woorſhip ſeruice, &amp; to reléeue my poore neighbours as hitherto I haue doone, and haue béene wel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Very wel quoth the Gentleman, be héere againe vppon Munday next and then ye ſhall vnderſtand more. The poore man (his duty doon) departed. The next Munday béei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next before <hi>Bartholmew</hi> day: the poore Man was come again, and brought with him a couple of fat Capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; about an houre or twaine after came this Churle very wel moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Gelding not déere of x. I. and behinde him was truſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a fat Buck, which he preſented vnto the Gentleman by one of his ſeruants. To be ſhort: he was willed to come in to the M. into a cloſe little Parlor, whither were called alſo this olde Farmer &amp; I my ſelf, whom it pleaſed him to vouch ſafe all courteſie and humanitie bothe in this and alſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, ſo that only wée foure were there, ſauing a young man attendant vpon his perſon. This doon: the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman began, fréend quoth he, what accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doo you bring
<pb facs="tcp:19011:27"/> againſt this poore man pointing him to the Farmer. Sir ꝙ. be none, I doo not knowe the man. No quoth the Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? except ye can accuſe him of euil: ye haue alredy condemned your ſelf therof, &amp; would doo me. Why ſo Sir quoth he? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sir quoth the Gentleman, for he cannot be guiltleſſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: that ſéeketh the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and death of a guiltleſſe man.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth the fellowe, ye charge me wrongfully, I neuer ſought any mans death. Sir quoth the Gentleman, he that ſeeketh to take away the ſuſtenaunce of a mans life, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> man ſay I, ſéeketh his death, &amp; that by ſo much a more cruel mean as it is a more cruell and fearfull death to ſtarue of hunger or colde: then it is to be quickly and readily diſpatched and murthered, and ſo ſoone rid out of payne. Ye haue quoth he, deſired to take this poore mans Farm from him, béeing his only ſtay, and haue ſo bidden for it: that I know he may not liue but in extreme miſery if he take it at your hands. Sir ꝙ. be, yée are the firſt great purchaſer y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euer I heard of this opinion. I haue ſix Farmes quoth he, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at their hands that doo think them ſelues bothe wiſe and woorſhipfull, yet was there neuer put vnto me ſuch a prob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem as this by any of them, yet drink I a C. l. a yéer by them abooue all charges. Fréend quoth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Gentleman, other mens dooing are no preſident vnto me, further then they ſtand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my dutie vnto God, and with the diſcharging of my calling, for he hath bidden vs by his prophet to ſtand vp and enquire after the olde wayes, and if they be good: then to goe in them or els not, which béeing ſpoken generally vnto all eſtates: how much more vnto them of my calling, and therfore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that ſuch hard &amp; extreme dealing might ſtand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dutie of euery priuat perſon, either vnto God or vnto their Countrye &amp; common Welth, or els with their owne aſſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce which I vtterly deny, yet could it not ſtand with my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor of any man of my calling. Firſt for the priuat perſon, &amp; to prooue that ſuch extre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e dealing ſtandeth not with his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards God, all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doo manifeſtly prooue wherin be ſo ſtraightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth vnto vs charitie, looue &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enignitie one towards an other, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the which a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare
<pb facs="tcp:19011:27"/> not ſay that he looueth God who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e he neuer ſaw, neither that he hath any faith, now what looue or charitie is there in him that letteth vnto his Neighbour a leaſe of hunger, want &amp; all miſery &amp; calamitie, &amp; ſo moleſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man, which God forbad to doo vnto the Dxe? The next, to wit, it ſtandeth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his dutie to the common welth, the very woord common welth, dooth ſufficiently ſhowe, for if a man liue in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth: he muſt haue ſome of the ioyes &amp; frutes therof, or els it is to him no common welth, namely traueling &amp; labouring fore therin, neither will be that a man bear any good wil toward that common welth wherin the ioyes &amp; ſorowes, welth and woe are ſo vnequally deuided, &amp; this ſtandeth not with the aſſurance of the common welth, which increaſeth by the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, looue &amp; concord, &amp; falleth &amp; decayeth by their contraryes.</p>
            <p>Theſe the two firſt béeing prooued, it reſteth me to prooue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſuch extreme taking &amp; exacting ſtandeth all with thaſſurance of the very partie him ſelf in euery priuat mans caſe, &amp; this ſéemeth ſtraunger &amp; harder to prooue: then the reſidue hath béene, but it is not ſo, namely vnto him that goeth with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> into the houſe of God &amp; there inquireth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for there he ſhall plainly vnderſtand that all is not cléerly gotten that is put into the purſe, for I my ſelf haue knowen a number quoth he, that haue raiſed iitj. times double y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues that their anceſters liued welthily &amp; woorſhipfully vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea &amp; before their death would fayne haue ſolde land if they had had any.</p>
            <p>The cauſe wherof is for that God who is not preſent nor called to councell in ſuch extreme taking: wil neuer be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nor giue councel or aduiſe in the beſtowing &amp; ſpending of the ſame, either to his honor &amp; glory: or els to their owne benefit, but giueth them ouer to delight in vile and vayne pleaſures, and to be gainfull and beneficiall vnto the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of voluptuouſnes and ſenſualitie and flatterers, whoſe fréendſhip endeth when the tap leaueth running, and when a mans owne liuing is gon and ſpent: there is nothing to be had at their hands but a mock or a flout.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:28"/>
            <p>But the Landlord that dealeth wel with his tenant hath of him an aſſured and vnfained Fréend, and that is prooued by the very duties and ſeruices which by our ancient lawes are incident vnto tenures. For what Fréend or what Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant ſhall a man finde that wil ſo abace him ſelf as (knéeling vpon his knées, his hed vncouered, his waſte vngirded, (hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his hands ioynt betwéen the hands of his fréend or Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) wil ſay I become your man and faith wil beare you, ſauing the faith which I owe vnto God and to my Prince. All which the homager dooth vnto his Lord, what may not a man hope at his hands that is thus allied vnto him, this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is farther veryfied by the ſaid honorable and ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Lawe of this Land which dooth giue vnto the Lord a writ of aid <hi>Pour file marier aid pour fair ſon fitz Cheualier.</hi> and doo binde the Tenaunt to ſerue his Landlord in the warres either in his perſon or by ſufficient Deputie. In all which things the Law hath an honorable conſideration to deliuer the Landlord from careful and heatheniſh deſire, and care to gather for the preferment of his Children, béeing already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſured where to leaue the ſame and neither charged with the gathering in or with the daungerous kéeping therof, either from the Théef or from his owne miſgouernment or intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce of life in apparail or in diet, which are moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous théeues. Alſo for the ſeruice of his Prince and his owne defence. It is not to tel what a maſſe of treaſure is ſpent vpon how few men that are but hirelings and come but for their hire for the which they euer think they doo to much and are alwaies ready to finde occaſion of quarrel bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (as I haue ſaid) no looue to the man nor ſeruing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but for the hire.</p>
            <p>But of the Tenaunt it is and hath béen wel prooued to be other wiſe and that in many a famous and memorable Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney happily atchieued by our Aunceſtors to their great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. Shortly this fréendſhip dyeth not, but with the parties, except it be through the Landlords great default ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſelling the land and ther withall his déereſt and moſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſured Fréends, orels by extream couetiſe and crueltie tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him all mean to liue able to be a Fréend.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:28"/>
            <p>Bothe which things are now of late yéeres waxen to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the more pittis. Thus it appéereth quoth hée, that ſuch hard and extreame dealing ſtandeth not with the dutie of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priuate perſon either toward God and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, nor with his owne aſſuraunce and countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Now much leſſe with our duties which excelleth theirs as far as heauen excelleth the earth, namely towardes God and our Country before whome wée ſuſtain ſo great an expectation of godlines vertue and all benignitie, ſo largely and ſo liberally rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto a deſire of priuate gaine and lucre from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which deſire would like wiſe detect vs of all impietie of percialitie and fauour vnto all vngodlynes &amp; wickednes, béeing the firſt cauſes of all our great gaine where through wée become Purchaſers.</p>
            <p>And therwithall he made an end and putting his hand in to his pocket: hee drew foorth two Déeds indented, and cauſing his Clark to read the one parte which was a leaſe for one and twentie yéeres after the olde rent, he ſealed &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it, and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our preſence deliuered it as his déed vnto the olde Farmer. The rich Fellow beholding this, took him to be very glad and prayſed God therfore, ſo great &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is the miſtery of godlynes (as ſaith Saint Paule) that euen they who in their déeds and woorks haue denyed the power therof, yet are they touched with remorce to reuerence it in others and to haue their déeds in admiration.</p>
            <p>This matter thus ended the rich Fellowe tooke his leaue and the next day I my ſelf hauing ended my buſines came a way alſo. A A A A A A Amen quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman.</p>
            <p>What meane you by ſuch a very long Amen Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> quoth our Hoaſt? <hi>Beati qui audiunt.</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> what mean you Neighbour quoth our Hoaſt? <hi>Nam miranda canunt</hi> quoth <hi>Pierce,</hi> I trow the man doteth quoth our hoſt, Nay Neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> I am affraid leaſt you doate your ſelf, why? quoth our Hoaſt, dooth this matter ſéeme ſo ſtraunge and maruelous vnto you? I will tell you another matter which is as true as this and of myne owne exerience alſo. I pray you let mée heare Neighbour quoth <hi>Pierce.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:29"/>
            <head>An other tale by the Hoaſt of a yung Gentleman that had morgaged his Land, comming to an other great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Lavv to vvhome bee offered to ſell his land of vvhome hee had great comfort. Chap. 16.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T fortuned an other time I was in Rent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at the houſe of an other great and rich O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficer towardes the Lawe, where I had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſoiourn certain dayes, during whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch time there came thether a yung Gentle man to offer his Land to ſel, and made an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer therof, vnto this man in my preſence, vnto whome this Woorſhipful Lawyer ſpake in this maner.</p>
            <p>Wherfore will you ſel your Lands (quoth hée) béeing an auncient poſſeſſion and a fair liuing? Sir (quoth this yung man) I am fallen into great det comming to my Lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was wiſe, and haue morgaged my Land for two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound, which except I come with in theſe ten dayes: I vtterly loſe my Land.</p>
            <p>You haue brought your ſelf into great extremitie (quoth this Gentle man) how be it, to ſel your Land: mée think a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard remedie therof, and great pittie if any other way mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght be taken, for hée that ſelleth away his Land: ſelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his beſt and moſte aſſured Fréend. Beſides that to ſel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way namely his auncient Patrimony and which hée neuer bought: is bothe ſhameful and ſlaunderous as to haue diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited &amp; deſtroyed his name, houſe &amp; familie, which is an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing &amp; the thing which the good <hi>Naboth</hi> the <hi>Ieſraelite</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed euen vnto the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for when <hi>Achab</hi> demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him his Vinyard for as much as it was woorth, God forbid ſaid the poore man that I ſhould ſel thée my Fathers Inheritaunce, béeing yet but a poore Vinyard: yet did hée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it to the loſſe of his life. Wée may read in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament how greatly God himſelf fauoured the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Inheritaunce &amp; poſſeſſion in their <hi>Tribes</hi> houſes, names &amp; families. For hée commaunded by <hi>Moyſes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19011:29"/> expreſly that if any man ſolde his Inheritaunce béeing Land or houſe: it ſhould return vnto him again in the yéere of <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> which was euery fiftie yéeres. Alſo that Women vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Lands and Inheritaunce were deuolute in default of heires males ſhould not marry into any other <hi>Tribe.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ꝙ hée) I wiſh you to haue a great regarde in departing from your Inheritaunce ſo great a bleſſing of God, for it is a great infamie &amp; reproche to be ſaid, an vnthrift and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caier of a houſe &amp; famely whether it were greater or ſmaller.</p>
            <p>Alas Sir (quoth this yung man) I am in greater diſtreſſe yée knowe theſe Merchaunts of London are harde dealcts with whome there is no mercie but for ready paiment, wel quoth the Gentleman, I will doo thus much for you, I my ſelf wil lend you an hundred pound which you ſhall repay by fourtie pound a yéere, and that I ſuppoſe you may eaſely doo ordering your ſelf wiſely, take that quoth hee &amp; offer it to the Merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t if happily he may be intreated to giue you a yéer or twain for the reſt vpon reaſonable conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yung man gaue him hartie thanks, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money was fetched down, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; deliuered &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce made accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly, which béeing doon: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yungma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> took his leaue &amp; hartily deſired me (although a méer ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger vnto him, (yet becauſe I was preſent &amp; a witnes of ſo great curteſie &amp; humanitie) to go with him to London vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Merchants houſe, which I alſo was content to doo, and hauing diſpatched the occaſion of my there béeing, and hauing like wiſe taken my leaue: to London wée came and to to the Merchants houſe wée went, when wée came before this Merchaunt the yung Gentleman began to intreat him as fair as hée could &amp; telling him of this good &amp; godly Lawyer and of his great compaſſion, his good councell and perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: deſired him to accept this C. I. in part of payment, &amp; to giue him a yéere or twaine for payment of the reſt. This Merchant hauing heard all the matter: now GOD forbid (quoth he) that euer a Lawyer ſhould heap coales vpon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants head, or that a Merchant ſhould not be as willing and as ready to doo a godly déed as a Lawyer, hauing receiued at the hands of God the like habilitie therto. And there withall hauing receiued the C. l. he tooke his owne bond for the reſt
<pb facs="tcp:19011:30"/> to be paid by x. l. a yéere, his firſt pay to begin after the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans C. l. ful paid, and deliuered vnto him all his Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and other aſſurances of the Mortgage, and making vs great chéere he let vs depart. Now when I would haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my leaue of this young Gentleman: I could by no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes forbid him to bring me on my way hitherward, as farre as <hi>Ware</hi> xx. miles on this ſide London, where he paid all my charges for that night, and the next day we tooke leaue eche of other and departed either of vs toward his owne. Thus ye ſée how frutefull was the good &amp; gratious déed of one man, and how it prouoked the zeale of an other to doo the like.</p>
            <p>A A A A A A A Amen (quoth <hi>Pierce.)</hi> Well quoth our Hoſte, becauſe you doo ſo hardly receiue my proofes: I will bring you more ſtore of them, and ſuch as I am ready to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifye againſt whom ſoeuer will deny their trueth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>An other tale of the Hoſte of a vvoorshipfull Lavvyer that made leaſes to all his Tenants of the Farmes they heeld for Li. yeeres. after a ſtraunge ſorte and alſo very vviſely. Chap. 17.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was (quoth he) in <hi>Buckingham</hi> Shire not very long ſithence, at the houſe of rich Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer toward the Law whom I could name if néed required, who during the time of my bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, made vnto all his Tenants leaſes of their Farmes, wherof I my ſelf am wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, preſent at their Sealing and deliuerye. The leaſes are for li. yéeres from the day of the date therof, the rent refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as followeth. Yéelding and paying vnto the ſaid Leaſſor and his heires yéerely during ſo many of the ſaid li. yéeres as thinheritaunce ſhall remaine in him or them, not ſolde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunged, mortgaged, forſaited, leaſed in reuertion or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe eſtraunged v. l. currant money of England, and yéeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and paying from and immediatly after any ſuch act doone by him or them or any of them v. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yéerly of like currant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo after the rate of other rents were they greater or
<pb facs="tcp:19011:30"/> ſmaller. Prouided allwayes, that the tenaunt ſhall not ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet nor let their ſaid Farme or any percel therof, without the aſſent and licence of the ſaid Leaſſor or his heires, of which reſeruation I aſked him a reaſon, whereunto his anſwere was this. Sée (quoth he) how hard a matter it is for young Gentlemen vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it falleth by the grace and gift of God to be Landlords and owners, wiſely to order &amp; gouern either their poſſeſſions, lands and reuenues or them ſelues. I know alſo (quoth he) that in the wiſdome, prudency and good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of ſuch: ſtandeth the happy and proſperous eſtate of a common welth, and her miſery in the contrary, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in my iudgement ought all men generally to wiſh, yea and to endeuour that the greateſt lands and poſſeſſions may be in their hands who bothe can and will order and diſpoſe the ſame to the honor and glory of God, and to the profit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common welth, wherin me thinketh ſauing reformation, the to often and to common tranſlation of poſſeſſion, is not the leaſt matter nor laſt to be conſidered, as well for the cauſes therof which are euill: as alſo for the effects thereof which are wurſe. The cauſes that make men to ſell their patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes and to ſpoile their inheritance, who knoweth not to be theſe, riot, game, whordome, delight in all vngodly pleaſures and paſtime of ſenſualitie, ſhortly the not fearing ef God, nor ſeruing him, and the not caring to knowe his will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, nor to liue therafter, theſe are the cauſes. The effects are theſe, firſt the ſpoyle of the land and the making it barren and bare of all the commodities therof, ſecondly the diſlodging and diſapointing of the honeſt Farmers and good houſe kéepers, for their ſakes that will bid more then they, without any other reſpect, and thoſe are commonly the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly, and from thence ariſeth infinit ſutes and controuerſies, maintenaunces, champerties and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>This cauſeth lands often to chaunge their tenaunts and inhabitants, and by that meanes breacheth &amp; diſſolueth one of the greateſt and ſureſt bonds of looue and fréendſhip that is or euer was, namely, coeducation, conuerſation and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, which hatcheth, nouriſheth and confirmeth looue and
<pb facs="tcp:19011:31"/> fréendſhip, not only betwéene men: but euen betwéene the brute and vnreaſonable beaſts, who hauing béene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tered long togither in one place, will not only looue and defend one an other: but alſo euen the very place wherin they were bred and nouriſhed, and they will very hardly be ſundred or dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen there from. And this is the very law of kinde, which can not effectually woork among neighbours, of whom ſome are dayly or yéerly flitting and giuing place vnto new, namely ſuch as will bid more the which commonly are the wurſer ſorte as hath béene already alleaged. Theſe are two effects. The third is the ſinceritie of Iuſtice &amp; alſo of diſcipline, bothe which it greatly hazardeth, namely for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> buyers and ſellers are Corelatiues, and that the one cannot be without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for that alſo the cauſes of ſelling &amp; ſpoyling of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies are ſuch as I haue alredy declared. Theſe things are right perillous in a common welth, and yet doo almoſte neceſſarily followe the to often and common tranſlation of poſſeſſion and inheritaunce, namely where it is by peny pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſe, againſt the which neuertheleſſe it is meruelous hard to foreſée and to prouide, I meane for heires and inheritors of Lordſhips, lands and poſſeſſions to continue in the ſame, béeing things that ſo many deſire to haue, yea often times ſuch as haue in their hands the bridle of libertie, or reſtraint of good and euill, and of the liues and manners of men, for what is there in all this earth ſo much deſired as houſes, lan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, Lordſhips and poſſeſſions, and to commaund ouer peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? What els is the end of all ſo many and ſo great trauels, watch, ſtudie, ſo many and ſo great hazards by Sea &amp; land, ſo many ſhifts, ſleights, deceite and oppreſſions, of all which this world hath béene, is &amp; euer wil be full, againſt all which who ſo will holde a thing of ſo great value: he muſt be well prouided and of great defence, and hath néed to haue in him ſelf the ſtrength, wiſdome, councell and iudgement of many, and ſo much the rather by how much his poſſeſſion is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, &amp; that for two cauſes. Firſt for that in his errour of life, fall and miſgouernment: lyeth the fall, ruin and decay of a number, what of his owne blood, what of his tenaunts, faith
<pb facs="tcp:19011:31"/> full fréends and ſeruants, Secondly for that his eſtate is ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect vnto many enemyes, of whom the greateſt &amp; moſte dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous is the flatterer the olde enemye of all man kinde, as the ſtory of our father <hi>Adam</hi> and mother <hi>Eue</hi> and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent dooth well declare. This mooued <hi>Iuno</hi> as <hi>Ouid</hi> fableth to commit <hi>Io</hi> her Cow vnto Argus to kéep, which <hi>Argus</hi> had an hundred eyes in his head, and therfore much a dooe had <hi>Mercury</hi> to deceiue him with all his ſwéet ſongs &amp; Muſick, for when he had brought one of his eyes a ſléep, yea diuers of them, yet waked diuers others and ſtood vpon their ward, and whether his face or his back were toward <hi>Io:</hi> yet he all way behéeld her.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>A reaſon vvhy Copyholdes, Cuſtomes and Corporations vvere firſt ordayned, and hovv that Pride &amp; Flatterye are the cheefe cauſes that many a young Gentleman com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſell his Lands. Chap. 18.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd ſurely in mine oppinion this mooued the wiſe and honorable fathers and Magiſtrates of olde time to incorporat ſo great liuings and poſſeſſions, and alſo to erect and eſtabliſh in Lordſhips ſo many coppy holdes and cuſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary tenures, as the moſte ſouereign remedy againſt pride and ſurcuydrie, which commonly accompanieth the priuate, ſinguler &amp; ſole proprietie, in la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, poſſeſſion, office or any other thing whatſoeuer, &amp; alſo a way and meane to furniſh the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon welth with many bothe able to deſerue wel and to doo good alſo glad and willing therto, vnto the which pride is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the only lot and impediment: or els of all other the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt as he vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flatterie attendeth, yea and in ſuch ſorte that he leadeth him by the noſe vp and down the houſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him to beléeue of him ſelf any thing, cauſing him alſo to delight no while in any one thing, whether it be apparail or the faſhion therof, place, perſon, dyet, fréend, ſeruaunt, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt or other thing whatſoeuer, and this as dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:19011:32"/> teacheth, is the high and ready way to the Vſurers hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, and from thence to the Extorcioner, who dwelleth hard by, of which twain by that time he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foorth his leſſon kindely: I dare be his ſuretie he will not be haſty to doo good to any good body, neither if he would ſhall he haue wherwith all, for either ſhall he haue no lands leſt him at all: or if he haue any, he ſhall be glad to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> déerer then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any honeſt man ſhall doo good thereon, ſo that in concluſion, bothe the Landlord and the Tenaunt ſhalbe miſerable.</p>
            <p>The cauſe héerof is Pride moſte and chéefly, as I haue ſaid, and often times youth, good nature, or peraduenture exceſſe of Pleaſure and Senſuall delights, where through young Gentlemen are often ſnared through euill company, béeing ouertaken ſometime by giuing their woord, ſometime through bribe of a little preſent mony, ſometime by one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, ſometime by an other, wherin men are ſoone pampred, uamely ſuch as are of ſmall experience and iudgement, and knowe not the falſe lures of the wicked and vngodly, aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt all which theſe Corporations and cuſtomes are of great force and a great defence, for in bothe theſe caſes: hardly can they be aſſaulted, much leſſe inuaded by any of the enemies aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt for that a corporation is neuer vnder age, as for example, Maior and Comminaltie, Deane and Chapter, Wardens and Fellowes and ſuch like, whoſe ſucceſſion is by election, their proprietie is ioint and in common, neither can one dooe any thing without the reſt, and therfore to flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter any one of them vaine, and to flatter them all very hard, namely mens Natures, Wit, Iudgements and Affections béeing diuers, and euery man willing to maintaine and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer his owne oppinion or his fréends. Pride atteinteth them not, for who is proud, or at the leaſt ſo proud of any thing, wherein a number hath to commaund as much as he, and without who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he can doo nothing, then béeing armed againſt Pride the Father of neceſſitie and néed: they are better frée<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to afforde their good woord or déed, and therfore in vayne were it to bribe them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:32"/>
            <p>But admit that any of them would be bribed, it were alſo in vain and would procure the euel wil of all the reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bribing them all which were heauie and harde to doo.</p>
            <p>So that in any competition made vnto ſuch perſons againſt any olde Fréend, Tenaunt, Officer or ſeruaunt: it is verie harde to preuaile except it be through his owne great miſbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour. And where it is betwéen méere Sraungers one of them againſt an other, there the beſt and moſte woorthie is ſure to ſpéed, for certainly and infallibly there is nothing in all this world ſo amiable, ſo belooued and fauoured as hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, vertue and godlynes are. Where priuate flatterie or briberie ſtand not in their light, as in the caſe of priuate O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wners and proprietaries: I haue alleadged that it both may and often dooth. And thus much of the Corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; of their effects. Now to ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtomes of Manours the very ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e or like in effect may be ſaid, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Inheritour of cuſtomary Land although hée be ſeaſed therof to him and to his heires: yet can hée not ſel it without licence of the Lord and that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly graunted by his Steward in open Court and there en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred, nay hée cannot ſet or let the ſame or otherwiſe impaire the wood or other commodities therof without the licence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forelaid.</p>
            <p>So great an entreſſe and commaundement hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, therin and yet not to the hinderaunce or preiudice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Inhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritaunce but <hi>econtra,</hi> namely that the ſelling, ſetting or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gouernment of ſuch a royall poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as land is: ſhould ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diuers, &amp; thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ripeſt &amp; beſt aduiſed, and not to be ſolde, waſted or ſpoiled through the intemperaunce of one fooliſh or vngodly man or woman ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for néed or neceſſitie or other wiſe for flatery or other fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or fooliſh affection what ſoeuer, wherin the Lord and his ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned Stuard and the homagers of the Court are Iudges. In all which caſes it may euidently appéer how great a care thoſe honourable and reuerend Forefathers had to enact and eſtabliſh the greateſt poſſeſſions in the hands of ſuch as were not like to miſregarde ſo great and high a bleſſing of GOD, the effects and frutes wherof haue béen many and great as from time to time proof hath verified and yet dooth, for it hath
<pb facs="tcp:19011:33"/> alwaies béen accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; yet is a right happy thing to be tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or Farmer to a corporation or enioy any commoditie vnder them. For woorſhipful &amp; honorable haue alwaies béen their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aling in ordering and gouernment of their Lands, liuingꝭ and poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſions, and of their Tenaunts and Farmers of the ſame. But chéefly and abooue all others to be Tenaunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince, who indeed is a Corporation, for from the Prince there can paſſe nothing but by writing vnder ſeale, neither dooth or can w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the conſeut of diuers of the moſte honorable and beſt aduiſed. Theſe (quoth hée) are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the reaſons that haue mooued mée to make theſe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes, and therin theſe reſeruations which vnto you doo ſéeme ſo very ſtraunge. For I ſuppoſe this to be a ſtrong meane to vnite the Landlord and his tenaunt togither, and to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terballaunce the one of them againſt the other in fourme of a corporation, orels as néer vnto the Nature therof as I could deuiſe. For by this meanes, if my heires or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at any time héerafter to prooue vnthriftie: his vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines ſhall not be ſo gainful vnto any man y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in hope to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his lands would therfore ſtrengthen his hands therein and by theſe meanes I haue left them mo Frends and fewer Flaterers. For hée that ſhall by his Lands without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Farmer: hée ſhall for the time make as good a pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſe as dooth hée that purchaſeth of a Woman her Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds lands while hée is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et aliue, or as hée that goeth to the Poul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie and buying there a Capon for two ſhillings putteth him into his bag, and when he commeth home he findeth there nothing but a Capons leg, for in this caſe of mine: the buyer buyeth leſſe then the Seller ſelleth by xix. parts, which me think ſhould kéep them from agréement vpon the price whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt either of them would fain make the beſt bargain for him ſelf, as the maner of all chapmen is. And for which reaſon Ieſus <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaith of them, that ſinne ſticketh betwéene the bier &amp; the ſeller as faſt as dooth a naile ſtick betwéen two ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in a wall.</p>
            <p>This way haue I thought to be ſtronger and better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then any entaile generall or ſpeciall, bothe which priuat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouetiſe hath found a way to deſtroy to the diſheriſon of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:19011:33"/> a good kindred and to the great decay of vertue and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and héerin (quoth hée) I haue doon my heires no wrong, for vpon this rent I haue liued content &amp; doo, &amp; if they prooue honeſt and vertuous: ſo may they doo, and then I haue left them inough, and if they prooue otherwiſe: then haue I left to much and yet to little to ſerue them alſo.</p>
            <p>Moreouer (quoth hée) I haue héer by prouided againſt the malice of ſuch tenaunts as abuſe the liberalitie of good Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords ſetting and letting ouer vnto the third and fourth hand racking and enhaunſing the things vnto exceſſiue and vnrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable, rents and ſuch as the Landlord him ſelf would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue doon for pure ſhame and pittie, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe béeing rayſed to his hand by others: is a perrillous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident vnto him at his return vnto the poſſeſſion therof.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard (quoth our Hoaſt) what a godly and Fatherly care this good and vertuous Magiſtrate had to preferre the hononur and glory of God and alſo the common welth of his Cuntrie and People, whereby it may appéere how hartilye to be deſired is the purchaſe of ſuch Perſonnes whoſe riches is the Treaſurie and Storehouſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, aſwel for the ſuſtenaunce of the ſame concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worldly and bodily prouiſion of tranſitorie things: as alſo for the furtheraunce and increaſe of Vertue, Godlynes and Pietie, Looue and Concorde.</p>
            <p>Hoe (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> lay a ſtrawe there for Gods ſake, marry Sir héer is ſtuffe indéed (quoth hée) héer hath béen a long diſcourſe indéed, and euen as true as all the reſt, with that I enterrupted their talke and ſpake vnto him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>The Author interrupteth Pierce, maintaining Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſercion, shevving that of late in his ſight he knevv a Lavvier gaue x. li. to the building of a Bridge. Chap. 19.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:34"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ather <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth I) theſe matters are not ſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nor ſo incridible as you weene, for proof wherof I wil (if it pleaſe you to giue me leaue) reherſe a thing which Imy ſelf did ſee and that no longer a go then Eaſter Tearme laſt. It fortuned that I went into a Lawyers Chamber in Sergeants Inne with a Fréend of mine who was Plaintiffe in a Repleuin in Bedfordſhire, &amp; béeing come into this Law yers Chamber and hauing ſtaied there awhile about our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines: there came in an ancient Gentleman of the Cuntrie, whome I know very wel by ſight and haue doon long, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e when the Maiſter had eſpied comming vp euen at the top of the ſtaires: hée ſpake to him as followeth. I knowe wherfore you come, go down again to my man and bid him come vp to mée, which the Gentleman did, his Seruant béeing come: hée took foorth of his Cubbord (which was vnder the ſquare ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble that ſtood before him) a bagge wherin was ten pound and deliuering it vnto his man bad him go down and pay it vnto the Gentleman, and if any of the golde lack weight chaunge it for him. The ſeruant went down and did accordingly. I thought verily it had béen the rent of ſome houſe or land that he had holden of him. But euen while I was in this thought: the Gentleman comming vp again gaue him humble &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thanks and that in the name and behalfe of a whole Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie yea of diners Shires. Wherupon I takeing occaſion to enquire farther of the matter: vnderſtood that he gaue that ten pound fréely towards the erecting &amp; building of a bridge, and that ſuch charitable déeds as this are no new things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. I ſooner wil beléeue this (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> béeing of a man learned in the lawes and whome Vertue and Learning haue preferred, then of the others that fiſhen for Offices w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the golden hook and neuer wiſt what learning ment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>Simons return to his matter again declareth of an other rich Officer in the Lavv vvho had tvvo Farmers, one rich and the other poore and hovv hee delt vvith them. Chap. 20.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:34"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith that our Hoaſt took holde again, ſaying y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hée had yet one other matter to tel, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hée would conclude. I was another time (quoth hée) at the houſe of an other rich Officer toward the Law, who dwelleth in Kent alſo and is a man of great welth, and one time of my béeing at his houſe as (I thank him) I haue béen very many times. There were two of his Tenaunts come to take new leaſes of their Farmes the lands béeing of equall rent &amp; value, but yet the Farmers not equall in welth: the one hauing béen bleſſed (as it ſhould ſéeme) abooue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other, for the one of them was very welthie and vpheld his Tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in very good repair &amp; offered the Lord at the firſt woord fortie pound for a fine for one and twentie yéeres. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was poore and yet his Tenament in decay, neither was hée able to giue fiue pounds for a fine, wherof the Landlord hauing challenged him and warning him to looke to it theraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: willed the other to lay down his fourtie pounds, which hée did without delay. The Gentleman when hée had coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it: put it into a bagge and fréely gaue it vnto the poor man, with theſe woords, (One of you beare an others burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) wher with the other was ſo farre from béeing all content, that hée humblie praiſed God, and gaue the Gentleman right hartie thanks therfore: and ſo hée ſent them away bothe very well contented. Since which time I heare of the poor man that hée is growen to great welth and of ſuch benignitie and hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie as are not many Owners or Landlords dwelling néer him. Thus (quoth our Hoaſt) I haue confirmed my firſt Aſſertion and haue ſufficiently auoided your reaſons and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples alleadged in diſproof of the ſame, and theſe haue I doon by Example and demonſtrations bothe moe in number then yours are: and alſo more euident, apt and proper vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purpoſe. That is not ſo Neighbour (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that your Examples were all or any of them true, which for the moſte parte I wil not graunt, yet are they per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler and cannot make any generall Coucluſion, beſides y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you tender mee an iſſue vpon two affirmatiues which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the grounds of law as I haue learned by mine owne
<pb facs="tcp:19011:35"/> experience deerly bought. For I have alleadged againſt you the generall Corruption of liues and manners beeing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect of libertie vnto exceſſe and diſſolution which I alſo haue alleadged &amp; prooued to be an effect of priuate deſire to pouch, to purchaſe and to wax rich, from all which cauſes &amp; effects conuertly my Argument is neſceſſary and infallible &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore béeing alleadged affirmatiuely it demaundeth a direct &amp; generall trauerſe to the effects, which effects béeing not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cauſes therof cannot be denyed, againſt all which matters you haue anſwered in the affirmatiue alſo, allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the examples of ſome good men, which whether they be true or not, I doo not greatly force without a generall denyal of that which I haue alleadged, although that for euery ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample alleadged you had brought fiftéen, and ſo is my firſt Aſſertion maintained and ſtandeth faſt, and yours vtterly diſprooued.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>The Concluſion of the Conference, and the preparation to the Queſtions beeing the ſecond Book. Chap. 21.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y this time it was waxen euen dark night &amp; our Hoaſt ſpeaking vnto <hi>Pierce</hi> ſaid vnto him Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth hée) wée haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſo very long to and fro that the night is ſtolen vpon vs, and the purpoſe of your com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming hither vtterly forgotten through our earneſt diſputation in theſe matters.</p>
            <p>Truely Neighbour (ꝙ <hi>Pierce)</hi> I cannot think this time ill ſpent, I would I had neuer ſpent time wurſe if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen God, and therfore quoth he, if it pleaſe you to lend me this v. l. I will be gon home, for I knowe the way at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. Neighbour <hi>Pierce</hi> (quoth our Hoſte) your v. l. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ye ſhall haue it with you but not to night, for hence ſhall ye not depart before to morowe God willing, and name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for this ſtraungers ſake, whom I wil deſire you to accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany for this night, for in his countrye I haue receiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:19011:35"/> folde humanitie, as partly ye haue heard, and therfore I gladly would doo him ſome héere to my power, and therefore this night or a conuenient part therof we will indeuour our ſelues to ſpend togither in honeſt mirth and exerſiſes. And therwithall I ſpake, and giuing our Hoſte harty thanks: de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Pierce</hi> that it might ſo ve. Who at my requeſt did ſoone condiſcend, and was very well contented therwithall.</p>
            <p>Then quoth I, ſeeing that we haue ſo well ſpent the fore part of the night wherin I my ſelf haue doon nothing but har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened: let vs agrée vpon ſome meane to paſſe the time with all after ſupper vntill bed time, no wurſe then we haue doon the time before.</p>
            <p>Now verely Gentleman (quoth our Hoſte) and that is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry well ſpoken, I beſhrewe him that diſagréeeth therunto, if it be my ſelf. Amen quoth <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> if it be I. Very well then quoth I, this is my order if it may pleaſe you. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Supper euery man ſhall put his queſtion and tel his tale in order, &amp; by courſe wherunto eche of the others ſhall ſpeak to wit vnto the queſtion ſhall giue an aunſwere of diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaying and vnto the tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall ſhew their good or il like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hée that telleth the beſt and wiſeſt tale to wit of high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt and beſt ſentence and putteth the ſharpeſt and wiſeſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion moſte tending to vertue and edyfying of the hearers or giues the wiſeſt and beſt ſolution: hée ſhall haue his breakfaſt héer to morrow at the charges of the other twain. Content with all my hart quoth our Hoaſt. Content quoth <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman. But to whoſe Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall wée ſtand heerin ꝙ hée? Truely ꝙ I, euen to the doome of our Hoſteſſe if it pleaſe her to take it vpon her, whervpon ſhée béeing called very wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingly vndertook it, ſo was the matter fully agréeed and our hands giuen theruppon. And then was the table couered for ſupper &amp; (our Hoaſt hauing him ſelf firſt giuen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to God) to ſupper wée went where wée fared right wel &amp; were mery, and when wée had ſupped: the Cloth béeing remooued, and thanks likewiſe giuen. After wée had ſitten ſtil and repoſed our ſelues a little while: I my ſelf began as followeth.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND BOOK, DECLARING THE</hi> Queſtions and Anſwers between the <hi>Author,</hi> the <hi>Hoſte</hi> and <hi>Pierce Plowman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>1 THe firſt Queſtion put by me, whether it be more pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per to vertue and godlines to giue or to lend, or to pay that a man oweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> anſwered, that of thoſe thrée to giue was the beſt, to lend was the next, &amp; as for paying that which a man oweth: he héeld it a dutie, &amp; in dooing of dutie there ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no Godlines, neither lyeth there any thank therin, &amp; that (he ſayd) appëereth by <hi>Chriſte</hi> his owne woords who ſayeth, that when we haue doon that which was our dutie: we are vnprofitable ſeruants, neither hath paying of debts any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimony of Godlines or vertue in the Scriptures of God, or by common experience among men, wheras giuing hath a name of vertue, namely of liberalitie wherof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh thus. He hath diſperſed and giuen vnto the poore, and his rightuouſnes remaineth for euer. Again of lending he ſaith. The rightuous is mercifull and lendeth, &amp; will guide his woords with diſcreſion, To be ſhort, liberalitie (which extendeth bothe vnto giuing &amp; alſo lending) is a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of God, who bothe giueth &amp; lendeth vnto vs his dayly gifts &amp; bleſſings, but borowe he cannot neither pay his debt. And ſo ſhortly paying of debt in his opinion no vertue ne pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of Godlines, for that it is a thing which God him ſelf cannot doo, and ſo the firſt twaine, vertues, and the third no vertue, but a duty.</p>
            <p>OVr Hoſte maintained the contrary, &amp; that to pay a mans debt is the moſte excellent qualitie &amp; vertue of the thrée, and moſte p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>culier and proper vnto the children of God, and that the other twaine are no vertues, neither deſerue that name, ſaue ſo far foorth as they are included within this, and for proofe therof thus he reaſoneth. What ſoeuer is or may be cauſe of euill: that ſame thing may it ſelf be ſaid to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. What ſoeuer act corrupteth or diſhoneſteth the dooer or the ſufferer therof, or els bothe: that act is or may be euil, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarywiſe, what ſoeuer act dooth not neither cannot corrupt
<pb facs="tcp:19011:36"/> or diſhoneſt the doer nor the ſufferer therof nor any other per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon: that act ſaith he neither is euill, neither by any means can be made or called euil. Lending ſaith he, oft times corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth and diſhoneſteth the dooer therof, namely for Vſurye, ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling the déerer for day giuen, bothe theſe are lendings in their kindes, and yet not any properties of Godlines nor vertue, But to ſpeak of the beſt lending and that which is ſimply w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of the regards aforeſaid. yet meaneth the lender to haue his things againe, and therfore what godlines is there ſaith <hi>Chriſte</hi> if you bid them to dinner y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> can bid you agains, what great godlines haue you ſhewed therin, and ſo much of lending. Gifts are giuen oft times to corrupt and to pernert Juſtice, and therby bothe the dooer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ufferer diſhoneſted. Gifts are giuen by the couetous in hope to receiue greater. Gifts are giuen by flatterers and clawbacks, namely ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and exceſſiue feaſts and banquets vnto Princes and great eſtates, to the end vnder their authoritie to ride vpon the poore and godly people, and to deuoure and ſpoyle the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of all others of the common and meaner ſorte, to the great oppreſſion of vertue and godlines, and to the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſe of all wickednes and vngodlines. Gifts are giuen in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of fréendſhip when nothing is ſo little ment, and ſo wickednes vtterly concluded therby. In giuing is oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vaine glory, and theſe two are the fathers &amp; mother of flattery. For where <hi>Thraſo</hi> is <hi>Gnatho</hi> wil be alſo, giuing vnto one fréend and not vnto the reſt, if a man haue many: procureth their hatred and enuye againſt bothe the giuer &amp; the receiuer. Shortly it ſtandeth togither to be a large giuer: and yet a moſte wicked and vngodly perſon, and thereof are great examples namely of <hi>Cateline,</hi> of whom <hi>Saluſt</hi> writeth that he was prodigall of his owne, &amp; deſirous of other mens. And of <hi>Silla</hi> that cruell Tirant he reporteth this, he would giue no man more frankly, lend he would alſo very liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but what ſoeuer he could borowe: he would neuer pay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Now vnto the third part, to wit paying a mans debt, and which (ſaith he) I call the moſte high and ſouereign ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the moſte proper vnto Godlines, and that for theſe
<pb facs="tcp:19011:37"/> cauſes. Firſt it neither corrupteth nor diſhoneſteth the dooer nor the ſufferer therof, for I am ſure all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil confeſſe that a man may honeſtly pay that which he oweth, and he, vnto whom he ought it, may honeſtly craue the ſame.</p>
            <p>paying of det corrupteth no Iuſtice neither I ſuppoſe can be prooued euer to haue doon in paying of det there is no oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of vain glory, for it is not the déed of a proude minde, whoſe propertie is not to acknowledg any good turn for that might charge him with dutie of acquitail wheron the proud and vngodly differ chéefly from vertuous and godly, for the proud may not ſéeme to haue néeded any mans good turn nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue vſed their help, bothe which things in paying their det they ſhould implicatiuely confeſſe to haue doon, and therfore are they aſhamed to repay what ſo they can borrow, for the Concluſion aforeſaid. And that ſtandeth wel with the ſaying of <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Sirack</hi> who ſaith that what ſo the vngodly can borrowe: hée accounteth it as if hée had found it, wherof the reaſon is this, although pure néed and neſceſſitie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtarin them oft to vſe this woord (lend) yet they vſe him for a cloke of diſſimulation as the effect ſheweth, for this is euident that there are but foure waies of attai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment or getting of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thing, for it is either giuen vs, lent vs, orels wée take it perforce, orels wée found it.</p>
            <p>So that whatſoeuer is lent vnto ſuch people either it is giuen or lent, or taken by force orels found.</p>
            <p>Giuen you wil ſay it is not, nor ſo ment by you, and you ſhall finde the ſame by him that took it at your hands, for hée wil neuer giue you thanks therfore, neither ſée you but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his hart.</p>
            <p>Borowed it was not vpon his behalf, and conſequently not vpon yours, howſoeuer you ment in departing therwith for except there be a borower: there can be no lender, for they are corelatiue and none can be without other, no more then there can be a Father without a Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, then if the one did not borrow: the other did not lend, hée borrowed not, for you ſhall finde that with his good will hée neuer ment to pay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Ergo</hi> you lent it not.</p>
            <p>Hée took not from you perforce for your ſelf deliuered it,
<pb facs="tcp:19011:37"/> ſo then if you neither gaue it, lent it, neither left by force, then there remaineth but a fourth, which is that you loſt it and hée hath found it, according to the ſaying of <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rack,</hi> for what ſoeuer a man findeth hée took it from no man neither is he bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to thank any man therfore, and that this is the manner of the vngodly: the Prophet Dauid beareth witneſſe where he ſaith. <hi>The vngodly boroweth and payeth not again, but the rightuous is merciful and liberall.</hi> Thus it appereth (quoth our Hoaſt) that who ſo truely paſeth his det: hée can not therin be called an euil perſon or be ſaid to haue corrupted or diſhoneſted neither him ſelf or any other bodie, and therin farre excelleth this quallitie bothe the other.</p>
            <p>¶ But now it reſteth mée to prooue (quoth hée) that this woord (to pay a mans det) dooth include bothe the reſt ſo farre foorth as they may or can be called vertues or properties of godlynes which I wil prooue in this order.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt I ſay, that whatſoeuer wée haue héer in this world: we haue it at the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful &amp; mercifull hands of our God, as lent and which hée may at his pleaſure take from vs, as alſo wée dayly ſée him doo. Then if wée haue nothing but that we haue receiued: (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith) wée muſt néeds confes wée are indetted vnto him therfore. How then can we pay vnto him our det for he receiueth no money? we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not feaſt him, for hée neither eateth Buls fleſh nor drinketh the blood of Gotes. It reſteth then that wée giue vnto them that are héer his Bayliffes and Receiuours for that intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and vnto them in whoſe perſones hée hath figured him ſelf vnto vs to wit vnto his poore and godly Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts that are héere vpon Earth among vs, vnto whome whatſoeuer wée giue hée hath promiſed to accept it, as giuen vnto him as a payment of ſo much det, a teſtimonie not of our merit: but of our woorking faith in his grace and mercie, and in this only ſence and meaning, giuing and lending are vertues and proper vnto the Children of God.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion put by our Hoaſt, was whether is the harder matter to make a Lord or a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon reaſon &amp; alſo by experience
<pb facs="tcp:19011:38"/> the harder thing: the harder is the dooing therof, a Lord (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hée) is greater degrée then a Gentleman, and therfore har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be made then a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> anſwered that I thought and knew the contrary by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for I know (quoth I) where a Churle by his purchaſe of a Mannour is become Lorde of a number better men then him ſelf, and ſo is hée a Lord and yet no Gentle man.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion of <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman was why poore men are not called to office of eſtate &amp; gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in common welths but euermore the rich and welthy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoaſt anſwered, becauſe quoth hée, the poore would be rich and ſo are not content with their preſent eſtate, but deſire alteration and chaunge and all ſuch perſones are more méet to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded then to commaund in a common welth. But of the rich and welthie it is clean otherwiſe, for they are alredy that which the poore haue deſire to be, and therfore content, and conſequently Frée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds and furtherers of peace and vnitie which is neuer nor neuer wil be where they haue authoritie in their hands that are not content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their owne preſent ſtate, &amp; ſo great hazard of the common peace lyeth therin.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by mée what is the reaſon that the Sonnes and Children of great purchaſers, namely Lawyers and Merchants, are commonly ſuch horrible and ſhameles vnthrifts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered that hée knew no reaſon therin but hée thought it a very ſecret Iudgement of God vpon the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rents that haue eaten ſoure Grapes and ſet their Childrens teeth an edge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoaſt ſaid it argued great equitie and conſience in their Children in that they ment to buy wit, and to pay as déer therfore as their fathers and fréends had ſolde theirs.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>THe</hi> next queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by our Hoaſt, what was firſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of giuing and wearing of mourning gownes &amp; garments for ſuch as are diſceaſſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered hée thought it was in fauor of our imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitle and weaknes, and for that reaſon: are not ſo prone and redy to wéep ſo ſore, namely rich widowes who cannot wéep ſo redily as a dog can make water, and therfore it was thought expedient that ſuch mourning were, and that ſuch as could not mourne for other buſines: there might be allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vnto them ſome honeſt and coullorable meanes to mourn by attourney, as wee ſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in matters of law, he that for other neſceſſary buſines cannot attend vpon his cauſes: is receiued by his Attourney, and of theſe great heires, executors and rich widdowes that are otherwiſe neceſſarily occupied and haue no leiſure to wéep: it was thought in like maner. Alſo it was thought profitable for the parties them ſelues for that it is an honeſt mean of publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wel of the widowhed as alſo of her great heuines, therfore wherby the more Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelers may reſorte vnto her, for in ſtraunge place a widowe is knowen from other by her mourning and ſorow.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by <hi>Peirce</hi> what differeth a couetous perſon from a Niggard. ¶ Our Hoaſt anſwered a niggard is affraid to want him ſelf, and therfore huſbandeth and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and oft liueth beſides his owne. But the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouetous is wurſe affraid leaſt others ſhould not want and therfore kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and engroſſeth all to defraude the hungrie ſoule, and to make the poore want bread.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by me why ſuch folke as delight in rich and coſtly apparel, and alſo in delicat and daintie meantꝭ and drinks, do not eat and drink in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> open ſtreats as they do weare their apparel. ¶ <hi>Pierce</hi> anſwered, becauſe that for their delicat fare: no body would honor or reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they gaue them part with them, which becauſe they pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe not to doo: therfore they holde it beſt to eat it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in doores and in ſeceret, but in their braue apparel there lieth ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor at the leaſt as they ſuppoſe, becauſe they ſe many y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> méet them ſtrike their ſailes therat although as great and the like reaſon in the one as in the other.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by our Hoaſt why the beſt and dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt meats &amp; drinks and ſuch as bréed and make the moſte &amp; beſt nuriſhment in the body, doo not alſo bréed the beſt maner but rather the contrary.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Anſwered, becauſe that commonly folke take to much of them, and haue ſo great felicitie therin, the rather that the miniſters of voluptuouſnes and ſenſualitie may thriue, but the chéefeſt and beſt reaſon ſéemeth to be this, that men may knowe that Godlines and vertue are not tied vnto meat and drink, neither doo conſiſt therin as, <hi>Chriſte</hi> hath ſaid. The kingdome of heauen is neither meat nor drink, &amp; to mooue vs therfore to eat and drink to liue, and not to liue to eat and drink.</p>
            <p>9 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by me, what poſſeſſion is the beſt and ſureſt, and leaſt ſubiect vnto rauin and violence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoſte anſwered, the beſt things &amp; the wurſt for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which is the beſt poſſeſſion, a man may cary farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without béeing robbed therof, and or that either man or woman offer to take it from him, and as it is of the beſt: ſo is it of the wurſt, for once (quoth he) I loſt a Gloue which was taken vp and brought after me.</p>
            <p>10 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by our Hoſte, whether beautie &amp; honeſtie may dwell togither in one houſe, and be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts bothe vnto one Landlord or not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PIerce</hi> ſaid, he knew no cauſe to the contrary, except the Landlord (quoth he) be a Purchaſer of Land, or a great builder or bothe, then Beautie muſt haue a Licence of the Iuſtice to kéep a Seller or a Bowling alley or an inordinary table or els all thrée, and then honeſtie muſt take a houſe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of.</p>
            <p>11 <hi>THe</hi> next queſtion by <hi>Peirce,</hi> what is the reaſon that ſome Women doo ſo curle and lay foorth their heres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe</hi> anſwere by our Hoſte, for that to be beardleſſe is in a man monſtrous, and to be bauld headed in a woman as in a trée neuer to haue leaues, or ground graſſe, and therfore leſt for want of ſhewing their heres they might peradum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be ſuſpected to be monſters: they make them ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry monſters in déed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dum vitant ſtulti vicua in contrarium currunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:39"/>
            <p>12 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by our Hoſt, what is the end and purpoſe of ſo ſtately and ſumpteous buildings of hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and ſo many Chimneyes therin now a dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe</hi> anſwere by <hi>Pierce</hi> phiſick and naturall, that againſt all ſickneſſes, namely <hi>Ethicks</hi> and <hi>Ptiſicks,</hi> all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting the ſenſes are holſome, &amp; alſo all things prouoking and cauſing appetite. Theſe delight the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, namely the ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, theſe ſharpen the appetite, for they argue hunger &amp; ſcarſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie within, neither is the ſmell of meat or drink hurtfull to weak ſtomacks, the Kitchin and the Buttrye béeing not ſo apparant, and euen at the firſt entrye as in olde buildings, but rather farre of, and hard to finde, and with ſome labour and exerſiſe except to him that knoweth which way they are. His reaſon <hi>oeconomicall</hi> politik, that it is a good defence aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt the haunt of Beggers, for there is no Begger that hath either experience or wit that will goe thither for an almes, and ſo, mony and charges ſaued therby.</p>
            <p>13 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by me, wherin differed flatterers from Crowes and Kauens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PIerce</hi> anſwered, they differ in this, that Crowes and Ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens will pick out a mans eyes when he is dead, but flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers will eat him while he is yet aliue.</p>
            <p>14 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by our Hoſte, wherin haue the rich of this world aduauntage &amp; prerogatiue abooue the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MY</hi> anſwere was, that their prerogatiues are great and many, but chéefly theſe that in the rich: vices get credit and eſtimation due to vertue, as for the purpoſe in them rob very and extortion is purchaſe, and lechery is ſolace, and ſo of the reſt as it pleaſeth their flatterers to magnify the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their folyes, and contrarywiſein the poore: vertues are ſlaundered, ſimplicitie and playne dealing are holden fooliſhnes, becauſe they doo not aduaunce.</p>
            <p>15 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by <hi>Pierce,</hi> what diſeaſe is moſts dangerous and hard to be cured.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> anſwered Pride, and a feuer Ethick in the third degrée, for neither of thoſe admitteth either cure or councell.</p>
            <p>16 <hi>THe</hi> next Queſtion by me, wherfore the Wiſe man had his ſonne beware of welth, and ſaid not ſo vnto him of pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoſte anſwered, for that welth is a flatterer, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doteth man and woman, neither can he ſhewe them their fréends, but pouerty dooth, and like as foule wether warneth a foole to take his Cloke: ſo dooth faire wether warne a wiſe man to doo the ſame.</p>
            <p>17 <hi>THe</hi> next queſtion by our Hoſte, who are they whoſe coſt and labour deſerue beſt thanks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THeirs</hi> (quoth) <hi>Pierce</hi> who the more they build the wur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe others are lodged, and the harder they fare and poorer doo liue, of theſe aſke &amp; enquire &amp; ye ſhall finde but to many.</p>
            <p>18 <hi>THe</hi> next queſtion by me, what the Poets did meane by the ſtory of <hi>Diomedes,</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they reported y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he had horſes whom he fed with mens fleſh, and that laſtly by <hi>Hercules</hi> he was giuen to be eaten of his owne horſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoſte ſaid, that by that tale as he thought, they mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame or like that they meant by <hi>Acteon</hi> &amp; his hounds, to with that to delight in exceſſe of vain pleaſures &amp; paſtimes, as in riding in Chariots or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great horſes or in ſuch ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maner to delight in hunting: requireth exceſſiue charges &amp; expeuces, wherby they are forced to deale hardly with all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haue to doo with them, with their horſes and hounds to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure bothe others &amp; them ſelues alſo at length, alſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much delight in ſuch vanities: profaneth the minde of man or woman, &amp; maketh them to wax barbarous &amp; void of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation, for els why ſhould they imagin a pair of Harts hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mans hed but for his wilde &amp; beaſtly minde.</p>
            <p>19 <hi>THe</hi> next queſtion by <hi>Pierce,</hi> what vice hathdoon God the moſte and beſt ſeruice of late yéeres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoſte anſwered Pride, for he hath béen a puniſher of
<pb facs="tcp:19011:40"/> all other vices, for what pecuniall ſtatute hath not he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and begged for the gaine therof, and whom hath he not inuaded therwith, and all to maintaine the filthie pride and exceſſe of a fewe.</p>
            <p>10 <hi>THe</hi> next queſtion by <hi>Pierce,</hi> what vertue hath of late yéeres doone moſte harm vnto men, &amp; moſte diſhonor vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THat</hi> hath liberalitie (quoth our Hoſte,) namely theirs who vſe to pleaſe others and yet depart from nothing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues but all at other folkes charges, which hath béene very common of late yéeres, bidding them ſpye out. &amp;c. This ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one in an others top, and brocheth ſo much brabble, ſute &amp; quarrell, this hath begotten vs ſo many reteiners, flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terers, promoters, maintainers, vnconcelers &amp; Sicophants, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hardly can any man account him ſelf aſſured in any thing that he poſſeſſeth be it land, farme, leaſe or other commodity what ſoeuer, that he ſhall not haue his title ſcanned &amp; ſearch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to the quick. This hath cauſed the Merchants trade &amp; his gain to be enquired vpon alſo, yea the very poore Artificer to be ſo ſifted: that hardly can he liue by his trade, to the great offence of God and trouble of the common welth.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Heer end our queſtions &amp; ſolucions, &amp; follow our tales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OVr</hi> Hoſte began his tale as followeth. It fortuned quoth he, within this twelue moneths laſt within fiue miles of this place, there fell a brabble betwéene two rich men concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning treſpaſſes by woordes &amp; ſpéeches, wherupon one of them ſued the other &amp; had demanded by action M. l. damage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I can not tell how, at length they were bothe content to put y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto two men of woorſhip their neighbours, and became bound in great ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes either to other to ſtand to their award &amp; order therin. The plaintif for their better inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto tharbitrators a copy of his declaration &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole iſſue, wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partie Defendant to ſome of the matter had pleaded not giltie: &amp; other ſome had iuſtified, wherupon thar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitrators hauing duely conſidered, and heard their allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for further proof of bothe their matters, ordered as folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the partie defendant béeing guiltie of diuers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behauiours by the Plaintife agaynſt him alleadged: ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19011:41"/> therfore pay two hundred fiftie pound vnto the common tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of fiue Pariſhes next adioining, to be there imploied and beſtowed at the diſcretion of the moſte honeſt and beſt of the ſaid Pariſhes &amp; vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> partie plaintif for all his coſts ij. d. this awarde béeing ſhewed and red vnto the parties they weare bothe highly diſpleaſed therat.</p>
            <p>The plaintif for that the Arbitrators had giuen that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Straungers (ſaith hée) which ſhould haue béen his and ſo haue excéeded the limmits of their autoritie and the tenour of his ſubmiſſion. The defendant thought him gréeued with the greatnes of the ſum &amp; ſo bothe the parties highly diſpleaſed.</p>
            <p>The Arbitrators maintained there awarde and order to be bothe iuſt and reaſonable. Firſt for the Defendaunt, they ſaid they were of dutie bound to puniſh him vpon good &amp; due proofs made by his Aduerſarie of his il and vngodly behauiour, wher neuertheleſſe they had qualified his puniſhment and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of his Aduerſary. As touching the plaintif and the ſum which hée demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the name and tearm of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends: their anſwere was that they ment it ſuch to wit an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends and that not only vnto one of them but to them bothe for they hoped that the Defendaunt by that time hée hath pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the two hundred &amp; fiftie pounds wil be better héerafter as concerning the like offence and ſo hée hath his amends, but what or how you would haue béen amended by the receit of ſo much money paid vnto you: if it might haue appeared vnto vs wée verely would haue adiudged it vnto you, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> could wée neuer perceiue nor be perſwaded to beléeue, for we neuer heard that honor, vertue, godlines and the exiſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are or euer were valued or valuable by money taking, but rather in departing therefrom, for as the laſt dooth ſhew a noble, gentle and a godly hart and minde: ſo dooth the firſt argue the moſte vile abiect and baſeſt minded perſon that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can be &amp; one in whome is vtterly miſpriſion of all vertue as wel witneſſeth S. <hi>Peeter</hi> vnto <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> wherfore (ſayd they) we thought that in this diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be your act: you haue vnto the world ſufficiently diſprooued whatſoeuer euil your Aduerſarie hath purpoſed to bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you as touching your exiſtimation or good name and haue
<pb facs="tcp:19011:41"/> ſhewed your ſelf in very déed ſuch a man as in the preamble of your declaration you gladly would be taken to be, and ſuch as if you be not alredy: wée verily think that the receit of all this and ten times as much more wil neuer make you, and therfore can be called no mends vnto you in the taking: but rather in the honeſt diſtributing therof, which we holde a iuſt and reaſonable Iudgement in all actions of ſuch nature.</p>
            <p>¶ With that the two parties drew foorth either others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation &amp; cancelled them bothe, and took hands and departed home great Fréends ſpite of the Arbitrators and of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and ſo ij. Churles were made fréends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THis</hi> tale béeing ended, <hi>Pierce Plowman</hi> would néeds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite with an other tale not vnlike. It chaunced one day (quoth he) while I was in my Councellers Chamber in the inner Temple: there came a woman dwelling about the Strand, and prayed his councell, and what action ſhe might bring againſt an other woman a neighbour of hers, that had ſaid to her in open preſence of diuers of her neighbours, that ſhe had alredy twiſe eſcaped the Gallowes. My Lawier aſked of her if ſhe had neuer in her life paſſed by a pair of Gal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes. She anſwered yes. So haue I doon (quoth he) I thank my God, and that ſometime when there haue béen a dozen hanged, and ſo I think haue you (quoth he). True it is Sir quoth ſhe. Then quoth he, ye cannot recouer for thoſe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, for they beare good couller of iuſtification, and alſo ſhew that ye haue had better fortune then poſſible many a better mans childe, and ſo haue I my ſelf alſo. With this anſwere y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> held her ſelf wel apaid, &amp; went herway co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THen</hi> began my tale. There is dwelling in <hi>Holbourne</hi> (quoth I and that not very farre from the place where I doo lye, a certain man whome I haue noted this long time to be a man of a ſtraunge affection, for béeing a man of great welth and therfore the méeter for company, yet if any freend or neighbour require him to goe with them to the Tauern, to the Ale houſe, to the Theater, to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Courtain as they term it, or to Paris garden or any ſuch place of expence: he vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſeth, &amp; after their return that willed his company: his
<pb facs="tcp:19011:42"/> maner is to go vnto ſome one of them, deſiri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him to tel him truely what hée hath ſpent ſince his going foorth, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing learned at him whether it be a grote or ſixpence, more or leſſe, hée goeth ſtrait vnto a Cofer that hée hath ſtanding ſecretly in his Chamber, which hath a Til, in the which Til there is a little clift, at the which clift hée putteth in aſmuch mony as the partie ſaid y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> had ſpent, and this til, hée neuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth vntil the end of the yéer, ſo that often times he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therin fortie ſhillings, oft times thrée or foure pound or more, &amp; this hée taketh and beſtoweth vpon his poor Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and vpon other godly buſines imployeth it.</p>
            <p>And vpon the lid of his Cheſt is written in great Romain letters, take from thy kinde, and giue to the blinde.</p>
            <p>This tale béeing ended, the night ſome what far run: our Hoſteſſe warned vs therof and that it was high time to go to bed, which wée were all contented to doo ſauing <hi>Pierce</hi> Plow man, who had yet one other tale to tel, and prayed vs to giue him the hearing, which wée graunted him, and then hée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</p>
            <p>¶ There is héer about (quoth <hi>Pierce)</hi> a Gentleman that hath enlarged his rent but not his land (where in many are very expert at this day) &amp; once vpon a time of my being in his houſe there came in a poore tenaunt of his, one that had béen long tenaunt bothe to his father and others his Aunceſtors, which poore man pittifully ſaid vnto him as followeth.</p>
            <p>Alas Sir (quoth hée) in your Fathers and Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dayes I liued wel and kept at the leaſt twentie Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e beſides Oxen and horſes, and now through your hard dealing with mée, I am not able to kéep twain.</p>
            <p>Wel quoth the Gentleman thou lieſt, for I haue béen bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to thée then euer my Father or Graundfather was, for where by thine owne confeſſion in their time thou didſt kéep but twentie Kine: now thou maiſt kéep two hundred at the leaſt, for now (quoth hée) through my fréendſhip thou maiſt be the common Neat hearde, and kéep all the beaſts in the Town.</p>
            <p>And thus our tales béeing all ended: wée required the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of our Hoſteſſe therin, ſhée ſaid that truely in her opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="tcp:19011:42"/> the Straunger (meaning mée) had tolde the beſt tale, and whereby ſhée had gotten moſte Example of edification and knowledge, whereby to help and inſtruct bothe her ſelf and others, and giuing mée great and hartie thanks therfore: ſhée gaue Iudgement that I ſhould break my faſt the next day at the charges of her Huſband and <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman, ſhée ſaid farther that to that man of whome I tould: the tale ſhée was Detter, if ſhée knew him to doo him good.</p>
            <p>¶ So héer wée ended, and went to bed, and the next day <hi>Pierce</hi> Plowman was vp very earely, and called mée vp and our Hoaſt, (as ſithens I haue learned his maner is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to doo) gathered vs all togither with the reſidue of his houſeholde, meiny, Children and Seruants.</p>
            <p>And hée him ſelf red vnto vs a Chapter of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then wée altogither ſang the fiftéen Pſalme of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and that doon to breakfaſt went, and after breakfaſt: I my ſelf would néeds pay the whole charges therof, and did, (notwithſtanding the awarde of our Hoſteſſe and their great inſtaunce to the contrary.)</p>
            <p>And when I would departe: my Hoaſt and <hi>Pierce</hi> Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would (whether I would or no) bring mée on my way to <hi>Doncaſter,</hi> and did, and there cauſed mée to haue great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment with out a peny charges for one whole day, and then wée took either leaue of other, and departed each of vs toward his owne.</p>
            <p>After which departure, vpon the way as I traueled: I reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> who ſaith. <hi>I was glad when it was ſaid vnto mee, we shall go into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> which I ſuppoſe he neuer ment by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Inne or hoſterie, where neuer the leſſe I may ſafely ſay I found it. And therfore ful true it is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Ouid</hi> ſaith, there is oftentimes a good fiſh in a wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter where a man would little think. Wée boaſt much of ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; nurture in the South partes of this land, namely in London, and diſpraiſe and diſpiſe the North as rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuil, but ſurely for mine owne parte (that am a Southern man and borne in Kent) to ſpeak indifferently for any thing that euer I haue found in all my trauel in bothe the par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es: I cannot ſée nor knowe why the Northern People ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19011:43"/> ſhould not rather pitie vs then enuie vs concerning either Godlynes, Vertue or good manners, for héer I haue ſpoken of the baſeſt kinde of people wherby it may partly approoue what hope there is of the Gentlemen, Merchaunts and them of the good Townes and Citties, for whoſe ſakes and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for all others I vndertook to gather and to reporte this little Conference, and with Gods good help and fauor haue doon it as neer accordant to the trueth as I rould, neither ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding therto nor taking therefrom, the deſire wherof cauſed mée to take the leſſer Iourneyes home warde and to write it by parcels at my Innes leſt I might haue forgotten it.</p>
            <p>And héerin I proteſt, that I haue neither flattered nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed any man, for my meaning is trueth and the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation therof, and therin is no flattery, for ſurely if I haue flattered any body: it is myne owne ſelf in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> that where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was perſwaded that pride had vtterly corrupted this whole common welth and had clean ouer ſpred it with his generation of all vngodlynes &amp; wickednes wherof all times and ages doo agrée him to be the father: ſithince this Iourney. I begin to hope y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> God wil haue mercy vpon vs, and hath, &amp; that hée hath reſerued vnto him ſelf a remnaunt as hée did in the time of <hi>Elias,</hi> for whoſe ſakes hée wil ſpare the reſt as hée offered vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> touching <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore the intent of this my collection thus appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: I referre my ſelf to the Iudgment of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whoſe hands it ſhall héerafter come, deſiring their good woord in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence therof, and alſo of my long and weary Iourney wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this labor was myne only rewarde.</p>
            <p>Beſéeching Almightie God of his great mercy and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to graunt vnto the ſame no wurſe effect then I haue ment therin, and that by the Appoſtles counſel, wée may con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider that wée are but Straungers and Pilgrimes héer in Earth, and that there after wée may order our liues &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation longing for our owne Cuntrie, content to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer, and to forbeare and glad to heare or ſée the thing that may be for our edifying, learning and knowledge to bée the méeter and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:19011:43"/> welcome into our Cuntrie which is the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> whither God for Chriſtes ſake bring vs all. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Foelix quipotuit rerum cognocere ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſas.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>VVho wil ariſe with mee againſt the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or who wil take my part against the euil Dooers.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19011:44"/>
            <head>THE APOLOGIE and Concluſion of the Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus ended is this ſhort Collection,</l>
               <l>Rude &amp; vnperfect for his want of ſkil:</l>
               <l>Who ſhould haue giuen it perfection,</l>
               <l>And would, if his might had been to his wil</l>
               <l>Or els if time had therunto ſuffiſed:</l>
               <l>To haue peruſed it and recogniſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But for aſmuch as I did fayle of bothe,</l>
               <l>To wit, of learning and alſo of time:</l>
               <l>And to let dye ſuch matter I was lothe,</l>
               <l>Though I ne could it duely enlumine.</l>
               <l>Yet for my God and for my Countries ſake:</l>
               <l>Me thought of force I muſt it vndertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And namely for the woorthy Shire of <hi>Kent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Famous of olde time for humanitie:</l>
               <l>As is to find in writing auncient,</l>
               <l>Beſides what dayly proof dooth reſtifye.</l>
               <l>Sith I was borne in her me thought of right</l>
               <l>I ought to bring this matter into light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ So ſtrongly ruleth looue the hart of man,</l>
               <l>Namely that looue which is ſo naturall:</l>
               <l>To doo his Countrie good in what he can,</l>
               <l>That his good hart is to be borne withall.</l>
               <l>For God requireth of a man but will:</l>
               <l>Although he want wherwith it to fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19011:44"/>
               <l>¶ Theſe are the cauſes why I took on mee,</l>
               <l>To be reporter of this Conference:</l>
               <l>Which I haue doon as heere is plaine to ſee</l>
               <l>As neere as I could followe their ſentence.</l>
               <l>Wherin if I haue fayled any whit:</l>
               <l>I pray you in good part to taken it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ For firſt touching the matter in ſubſtaunce,</l>
               <l>The ſpeakers are the Authors and not I:</l>
               <l>As for the order in deliueraunce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>I put it in the Readers courteſie.</l>
               <l>To mend it, or to take it as it is:</l>
               <l>For he is wiſe that dooth nothing amiſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Aut bibe, aut abi.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
